<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Phisicke for the soule verye necessarie to be vsed in the agonie of death, and in those extreme and moste perillous seasons, aswell for those, which are in good health, as those, which are endewed with bodily sicknesse. Translated out of Latine into Englishe, by H. Thorne.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1567</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19893A.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106667</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842380</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842380</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7028</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09620)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7028)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 668:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Phisicke for the soule verye necessarie to be vsed in the agonie of death, and in those extreme and moste perillous seasons, aswell for those, which are in good health, as those, which are endewed with bodily sicknesse. Translated out of Latine into Englishe, by H. Thorne.</title>
                  <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407. De patientia et de consumatione huius sæculi, de secundo advento. aut</author>
                  <author>Thorne, Henry, fl. 1567-1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 69, [3+] pages   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Denham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1567?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes a translation, by Henry Thorne, of: Chrysostom, St. John.  De patientia et de consumatione huius sæculi, de secundo advento.</note>
                  <note>Includes tables.</note>
                  <note>Folio 61 misnumbered 56.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19895a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Slight print show-through; folios 103 mutilated; all after I6 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Phiſicke for the Soule,</hi> verye neceſſarie to be vſed <hi>in the Agonie of death,</hi> and in thoſe extreme, and <hi>moſte perillous ſeaſons,</hi> aſwell for thoſe, which are <hi>in good health, as thoſe, which are endewed with bodily ſickneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latine into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe, by H. Thorne.</p>
            <q>Quid prodest homini, ſi vniuerſum mun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> tur, animae autem ſuae detrimentum pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>What ſhall it man auaile, if all the worlde, he gaine.</l>
               <l> And after that of his owne ſoule, he do the loſſe ſuſtaine?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Pervſed, and allowed, according to the Queenes Maiesties Iniunctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IMPRINTED AT LONDON, by Henry Denham.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <head>
               <pb facs="tcp:7028:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7028:2"/> 
               <hi>Phiſick for the Soule,</hi> very neceſſary to be vſed in <hi>the Agonie of death, and in <hi>theſe extreme and moste</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous ſeaſons, as well for</hi> thoſe that are in good health, <hi>as thoſe, which are endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>with bodily</hi> ſickneſſe.</hi> Tranſlated out of Latine, into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhe, by H. Thorne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iſeaſes trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our bodies, and corporall death, ſhak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our mindes with ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rible feare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much that of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wee tremb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the recy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of them. Mans natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had leauer not to bee at all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> cannot but waxe pale, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> when theſe ſickneſſes doe ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> déede, no calamitie can b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7028:3"/> more cruell, none more horrible, none more houge, then the ſickneſſe of the ſoule, and the death and deſtruction therof. Euery man abhorreth, euery man deteſteth and eſchew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by Sea and lande, puniſhments, pitifull labors, diſeaſes, and this bodily death. But we ought much more to endeuor our ſelues, to auoide and leaue off the occaſions of thoſe euilles, that is to wit, ſinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, and that we ought to dread the heauie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, which wée prouoke againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers and manifold offences.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our bodily health is ympaired, we ſtraigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wayes poſte vnto the Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, here we ſpare for no charges, we leſſe eſtéeme all things then the ſafegarde of our life, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure medicines &amp; remedies at a great price, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the intent, that this oure earthen veſſell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otſheard, mought be againe repaired, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thin ſhort ſpace after notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>die to breake. Why doe wée not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>die and carefulneſſe, deſire, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies againſt the diſeaſes, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Soule, béeing farre more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore perillous? For what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an take, if he did abounde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the whole worlde, and
<pb facs="tcp:7028:3"/> did liue a thouſand yeares togithers, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ioyed continual and moſt exquiſite pleaſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of this lyfe, and were not incumbred wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any trouble of ſickneſſe, or other calamiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> But yet in the meane while, his ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> infected with the deadlye gilt and poyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinne, and oppreſſed with the cruell tir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Sathan, God was diſpleaſed at him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he moſt certainly knewe, that after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of this life, hée ſhoulde ſuffer eternall de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and damnation both of body &amp; ſoule? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt ſaid: Watch. For ye know ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther the day, nor yet the howre, in the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſonne of man ſhall come. And le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhoulde followe light, friuolous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things, the good &amp; moſt profitable no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, he ſhoweth vs a moſt compendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine, and ſure way, to aſpire vnto tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> citie, where as he ſayeth: Séeke ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> kingdome of heauen, and the righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereof, and all theſe things ſhall bée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtred vnto you. The cares of lyuing, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eſtabliſhing of oure wealth, &amp; other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yea, many times fooliſhe, bruckle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting, which nothing preuaile vs, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſions of verie greeuou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and moſt wicked offences, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7028:4"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> vs night and day.</p>
            <p>But in the ſéeking &amp; getting of heauenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ches, what thing is more flow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hat more negligent? what more vnadui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>? what more fooliſh? What blindneſſe or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>neſſe, I pray you, ought more to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Whilſt wee liue in good health, ſcarce <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch as one little thought at any time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>meth in our mindes of the lyfe to come, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of that our temporall death. But when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> we lie downe and are ſicke, death nowe (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were) knocking at oure dores, when wée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ould ſtande vp in the front and fight, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt we begin to thinke of the taking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r weapons againſt Sathan, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endment of oure life. Theſe things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ufficient argument to prooue, that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dued with a ſlender and weake fayth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at we are little exerciſed in the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arfare. God be mercifull vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut truely euerie age is méete to amend, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d no repentance commeth to late, ſo that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne before the ende of this lyfe. Yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll and earneſtly giue admoniſhment, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>an do linger and deferre the doing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, vntill this laſt and moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or euen they which are ſtrong
<pb facs="tcp:7028:4"/> and in good health all their life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> haue prepared and furniſhed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt this howre of departing, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and with much adoe, ſcarcely defende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues, from the deceiptes, guiles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and inuaſion of that moſt paſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubtill enimie: what ſhall bée d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> thoſe, which beeing voide of al feare of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knowing not howe to repent, haue li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> filthie, and diſſolute, and naughtie life, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I beſech you ſhall they fight, how ſhall th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſiſt?</p>
            <p>Now therfore, ſeeing that there is a gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> multitude and aboundance of people eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where, and ſéeing that the Miniſters of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Goſpell are not néere at hand in all pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> neyther are able to performe their dilige<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or office alwaies, and vnto all men, we of good and godly minde, willing to profite a men, haue written this waye and forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> comforting, inſtructing, and admoniſhin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſick, collected out of the worde of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their commoditie &amp; profite eſpecially, which<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are yet ignoraunt, and not inſtructed ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ently in the Sentences of holy Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuch occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that they hearing thoſe thing read vnto them, maye thereof conceiue tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7028:5"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſolation or comfort, leaſt they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alſe hearted, ſhould diſpaire and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in the bitter Agonie of death.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is chiefly neceſſarie for the Sick, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de the paines of the body, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> temptations, wherwith he is peſtered.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An therefore lying on bed by vehemencie of ſickeneſſe, and béeing in daunger of death, is aſſayled and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with dyuers and gréeuous te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations, againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which he muſt contende and ſtriue. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of all, this is a moſt bitter temptation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen the moſt horrible Image of death bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g (as it were) before our eies, wée thinke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at we muſt forſake and leaue the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ctable and pleaſaunt light of this lyfe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll our deare kinſfolkes and friends. Finally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat wée muſte héere forgo all our pleaſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> welbeloued things. And anon, our ſinnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mmitted againſt the will and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ment of God, doe preſent themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vs, ruſhing in with a great violence, are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7028:5"/> cléerely renued, and waxe raw againe, and they ſéeme to be many moe in number, and more gréeuous, then euer they did before, ſo that they maruellouſly torment, vexe, and trouble our conſcience. Here death, Gods iudgement, Hell, damnation, feare, and trembling, like an hoſte gathered togither, torment our olde man, with moſte violent and troublous ſtormes of verie great dolors and terrors, and doth aſſault and ſhake our hearts with moſte vehement ingines of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and heauineſſe. There will be great daunger in thoſe Agonies and troubles of the minde, if oure heart bée not eſtabliſhed with a ſure and conſtant faith, leaſt we now béeing weakned and wearied with the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and greatneſſe of temptations, do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire. For thoſe things, which come in our mindes when we are ſicke, ſéeme to be moſt horrible and gréeuous, and for none other cauſe, then that oure faith is verie little and doth wauer, neyther yet is ſo ſtrong, that truſting vnto the worde of God, is able to apprehende that vnmeaſurable and ineaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable treaſure and riches of God the ſonne, that is to wit, the remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes through Chriſt, the reſurrection of the fleſhe, that
<pb facs="tcp:7028:6"/> moſt pleaſaunt and exoptable felowſhip of all the elect, and the lyfe euerlaſting, and that all theſe things are giuen vs fréely in Chriſt, and for Chriſt.</p>
               <p>We ought daylie to exerciſe our ſelues in theſe Articles of our faith, and to faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them in vs diligently, pondering &amp; weighing them in our mindes. Alſo we ſhoulde oftentimes come vnto the Sacrament,<note place="margin">Synaxis.</note> or the Table of the Lords ſupper. But we muſt firſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trie, faſhion, and prepare our ſelues. For we ought eſpecially to beware of this, that we meddle not with the moſt royall Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> or of thankeſgiuing, with vnwaſhed mindes, and ſpotted conſciences.</p>
               <p>It is truely a ſhamefull matter, and much to be lamented, that this many yeares this Sacrament of the body and bloude of Ieſus Chriſt, hath béene ſuperſticiouſly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and of ſome other it hath béene hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnreuerently, and little according to the worthineſſe thereof, in ſo much that of ſome Heretikes it hath béene vtterly contemned and diſpiſed. The preſent puniſhments and afflictions doe ſufficiently declare vnto vs, how haynouſly they offended therein, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of S. Paule foretold vnto the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:7028:6"/>
               <p>This Sacrament ſurely is a great and marueylous pledge of his eſpeciall loue and ſingular mercy towards vs, which he would haue to be teſtified and declared vnto vs, in that his laſt Supper, how that he adioyneth vs vnto him, as his myſticall members, that we may know and vnderſtande, that we are beloued, regarded, and preſerued of him. Thus doe godlye mindes determine, that Chriſt is effectuall in vs. I woulde to God we would learne to conſider in our mindes, the worthyneſſe of this ſo royall a gifte, that we might be therefore thankfull, and when we aduaunce &amp; lift vp our faith, we mought then alſo haue a reuerent feare, and thinke how deteſtable an offence and ingratitude is, and what horrible puniſhments will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the prophanatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or vnholy vſing of this ſo worthie a myſterie. And it is not to bée thought, thoſe moſte grieuous threatnings, which Saint Paule maketh mention off, to be vaine, and of none effect. For God is alwaies true. And I ſuppoſe aſſuredly, that the greateſt parte of thoſe publicke euilles, which haue béene in our dayes, are to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted vnto the diſorderly, and groſſe vſing of that moſt holy pledge. Let vs therefore
<pb facs="tcp:7028:7"/> oftentimes prepare our ſelues, to come vnto the Communion Table, with feruent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of vertue and holyneſſe, that our mindes béeing refreſhed and comforted with that heauenly foode of the ſoule, faith and charitie maye bée daylie increaſed and ſtrengthened in vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Articles of our Faith, are diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be conſidered of the Sicke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee ought alſo furthermore to remember, and alwayes haue in our mindes, all the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our Catholike Faith. But foure eſpecially are dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to be conſidered, and to be poured into vs, by often repiticion, in the Agonies and troubles of death, that is to ſaye, the communion of Saintes, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes throughe the bloode of Chriſt, the riſing againe of the fleſhe, and the eternall lyfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Wherefore ſickneſſes ar ſent vnto vs from God.</head>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7028:7"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hen as death is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſhment of ſinne: Euen ſo diſeaſes are many times ſent vnto vs from God, for our ſinnes, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing is manifeſt by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye teſtimonies of Scripture, as in <hi>Ioan. <hi>5.</hi> Pſalme. <hi>88.</hi> Deut. <hi>28. 2.</hi> Reg. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </hi> We are alſo often afflicted, that oure fayth thereby mought be tryed. For then ſurely a man may ſée, how much wée loue God, how muche we truſt in him, when we are afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and oppreſſed with ſome gréeuous croſſe. Then here aboue all things ſée, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vnfaynedly, turning thy whole heart, minde, and ſenſes vnto God, that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt confeſſe and bewayle thy ſinnes before him. For ſinne is the onely cauſe, why we deſerue the moſt iuſt wrath, &amp; heauie plague of God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20.</note> And thou ſhalt gather out of Saint Iohn his Goſpell, the moſt aboundant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, off abſolution or remiſſion of ſinnes, which Chriſt hath inſtituted and left vnto his vniuerſall Church. This vnmeaſurable treaſure, is opened and offered vnto thée dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye. Chriſt ſayth, receiue yée the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18.</note> whoſe ſinnes ſoeuer yée forgiue, they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen them, and whoſe ſinnes ſoeuer yée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:8"/> they are retained. Now when we haue deſired and obtained forgiueneſſe of our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déedes, without all queſtion to the contrarie, the paine and griefe or affliction alſo béeing on vs, either will ceaſe and leaue vs, either will redownd vnto the ſaluation of the ſicke body, according to the paſſing good will and pleaſure of almightie God. For thou muſt be throughly perſwaded, that thou nothing doubt herein, but that the paine or croſſe (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it ſéeme vnto the fleſh a verie heauie yoke and burthen) is a méere fatherly rodde and correction, whereby God doth withhold, and call backe thée, his childe, from commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſinne, entiſing and alluring thée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. God verily loueth vs with a feruent zeale, hée willingly tendereth our ſaluation, and worketh all things vnto this ende and purpoſe, that he may correct vs, and bring vs vnto good. For looke whome he loueth, him doth he correct, him doth he chaſten &amp; afflict in this world, leaſt after this lyfe, he ſhould be tormented with the euerlaſting paine of vnquenchable fire. And wauer not, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thy ſelfe moſt certainely, that God is thy moſt louing Father, and much deſirous of thée, howſoeuer he ſeeme to be angry with
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7028:8"/> thée. This is not the wrath of a Tiraunt, and an executioner, but of a father intéerely louing vs, which would not that we ſhould be loſt, and caſt awaye: but that we béeing corrected ſhoulde amende, and obtaine ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. This is a moſt certaine truth, if ſo be that we, whoſe faith is ſo weake, can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue it. Firſt of all therefore, aſke thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe and remiſſion of all thy ſinnes, but through Chriſt, and with a verie repentant heart, that thou mayeſt well accorde with God, that thou mayeſt find him pacified and mercifull vnto thée. After this done, thou mayeſt alſo beſéech him to delyuer thée from the affliction, which troubleth thée. So doth <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> teach vs, whereas he ſayth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 38.</note> My ſonne deſpiſe not thy ſelfe, in thy ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but pray vnto the Lorde, and he ſhall heale thée. And ſo doth the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> praye. Remember not (O Lorde) our olde iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, let thy mercies ſpéedily preuent vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79.</note> help vs O God our Sauior. Conuert vs O thou Lorde God of power, ſhewe vs thy louing countinance, and we ſhall be ſafe, how long wilt thou be angrie?</p>
               <p>Firſt he deſireth forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes, that he might be iuſtified by the grace of god.
<pb facs="tcp:7028:9"/> Next he entreateth againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of God, And when thou prayeſt for the deliuerance and eaſement of the croſſe, which oppreſſeth thée, thou ſhalt alwayes put to this additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Thy moſt bleſſed and holy will be done. For we cannot better ſée vnto our ſelues, then ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our moſt faithfull Father, of his endleſſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, wiſedome, and infinite goodneſſe, which neuer turneth his eies from vs, but with all diligence taketh care of vs, which knoweth the number of the heares of our heads,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> which doth quicken, comfort, cheriſhe, couer, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, preſerue, and defend all things, which helpeth and prouideth for all men, much more, and farre better, then any creatures can bée able, yea, to wiſh for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:7028:9"/>
               <head>There be three things, which torment vs moſt greeuouſly, and cruelly, and doe trouble our mindes in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonie of death, that is to wit, Sinne, Death, Hell, or Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Sinne</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen thoſe Sinnes come in our mindes (we lying ſicke) wherein wée haue wickedly &amp; noughtily paſſed ouer our lyues, wherby we haue very gréeuouſly offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded both God, and our neighbor: we are ſtriken with great feare and ſorrow, euen as S. Paule ſayeth vnto the <hi>Romaines:</hi> Indignation &amp; wrath,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> tribulation, and anguiſhe ſhall come vpon the ſoule, of euery man that doth euill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Death.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Dam, our fleſh, dieth very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyllingly. Wherefore when death approcheth neere, mans heart is altoo ſhaken wyth great dolors and heauineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:10"/> which no tongue is able to expreſſe. For our fearefull affection, and oure naturall man, dreadeth miſerablie, leaſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when he is once dead and buried vnder the earth, he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer returne againe and liue, but ſuppoſeth that he is vndone for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Hell fire, and Damnation.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen thoſe things come (as it were) before our eyes, then man feareth, leaſt he bée vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly caſt away from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, and ſéeth none other thing in himſelfe, but euerlaſting death. Wée haue neede therfore of a good courage in this caſe, and of a ſtrong and valiant heart, that there appeare in vs, no point of cowardneſſe, and deſperation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶A Prayer for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt mercifull God, and moſt louing Father, I beſéech thée aide vs, and graunt that we, which bée yet in good health and ſafetie, may learn to feare
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7028:10"/> and dreade thée, may loue and imbrace thy holy worde, and that we may ſet thée before vs, as a ſcope and marke whervnto we may direct all our doings, and that we being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes mindefull of the moſt bitter agonie of death, may ſo prepare &amp; arme our ſelues, that we maye order all our deedes to thy glory, as doe the godly, which feare thée, and that we may in the ende obteyne euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting lyfe. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>What is to be done, when Sinne doth vexe, and ſtirre our conſciences.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinke with thy ſelfe, that the ſonne of GOD came downe from heauen into the loweſt partes, and was made man, he tooke vpon him thy ſinnes, and the ſinnes of the whole worlde, hée willingly dyed on the croſſe for them, and made full ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for them all, ſuffering for thy ſake moſt gréeuous paines.
<pb facs="tcp:7028:11"/> The moſte precious blood of Chriſt was ſhed for thy ſaluation, and thou art parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his death, if ſo be that thou conſtantly beleue on Chriſt, that he died as wel for thée, as for Peter and Paule. And thou oughteſt not to doubt any thing at all, but that hée dyed as effectuallye for thée, as for Paule. Thou art baptiſed throughe the death of Chriſte. This thing ought to comforte thée, this thing ought to lift vp, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy minde. For ſéeing that thou art baptiſed through the death of Chriſt: his death ſhall ayde and ſaue thée, through his death thou ſhalt not die in thy ſinnes, but through his death thou ſhalt vndoubtedly obteine forgiueneſſe of them all, and in the ende through Chriſt his death thou ſhalt riſe againe vnto a new, and euerlaſting life. For baptiſme is a ſure token,<note place="margin">Babtiſme</note> pledge, and ſigne of Gods grace and fauour, wherein thou art reconciled vnto God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou maieſt haue a ioyous and quiet conſcience through him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> for the forgiueneſſe of thy ſinnes by Chriſt his reſurrection. And he certeinlye ſpeaketh vnto thée in the inſtitution of his laſt ſupper, where as he profeſſeth, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, that his blood was ſhed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7028:11"/> of ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Now therfore although thou haue not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued an vpright, and pure life, in eche reſpect, yet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> there is no cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt diſpaire, but ſpéedily call vpon the name of of the lorde, without ceaſſing, and thou ſhalt bée ſafe. And thus begin thou to ſaye: O moſte mercifull GOD,<note place="margin">A prayer.</note> O father of all compaſſion, father of oure lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, bee mercifull vnto mée a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, haue compaſſion on me a poore wretch, and make haſte to helpe mée, for that moſt bitter, yea moſte precious paſſion, and death of Ieſus Chriſt, thy onely begotten ſonne, and our onely redéemer, and ſauior. Enter not into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with thy ſeruant oh lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.</note> deale not with mée according to my deſertes, neyther rewarde me according to mine iniquities, but receiue me for thine infinite, and endleſſe goodneſſe, and mercies ſake. I a wretch, and ſéely creature, am in thine hand, power, and daunger, oh moſte mightie, and mercifull God, oh moſt louing father, caſt mée not awaye vtterly refuſed in miſerie. I am thine, whatſoeuer I am. No man can comfort mée, no man can help
<pb facs="tcp:7028:12"/> me beſides thee onely. Thou art the true propulſour, &amp; driuer awaye of all miſchiefe from men. Thou art the moſt ſure, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die helpe, ayde, ſuccour, and defence. Thou art the moſte ſtrong tower. Thou art O God our hope,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.</note> and ſtrength, thou art a very preſent help in trouble. In thée O Lorde do I put my truſt, let me not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded, let me neuer bee aſhamed, my hope béeing in vayne, but deliuer me in thy righteouſneſſe. Bow downe thine eare to mee, make haſte to deliuer me. And be thou my ſtrong rock, and houſe of defence, that thou mayeſt ſaue mée. Thou art my ſtrong rock, &amp; my caſtle. Thou art my lorde, my porcion is in thine handes. Lighten thy face vpon thy ſeruant, and ſaue me O lorde in thy mercie.</p>
               <p>Further, thou, that art ſick, muſt be chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſhed of this point, that thou think not what ſinnes thou haſt committed, but rather haue before thine eies to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template, and looke on, the image of Chriſt, his moſt holeſome, &amp; precious death. Faſten it ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in thy minde, and thorowly perſwade thy ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53. <hi>Math.</hi> 8.</note> that thou art not now oppreſſed with thy ſinnes for Chriſt, and that they are all layed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſhoulders, which taking them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7028:12"/> vpon him, hath made ſatiſfaction and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 32. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> ſo that he will neuer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them vnto vs, but will fréely forgiue them all, euen as we ſaye in the articles of our faith: I beleue the remiſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The teſtimonies of ſcripture for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes throughe Chriſt, muſt be diligently repeated vnto the ſick, wherof, I haue here vnder recited ſome, that they may be in a readyneſſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eholde the Lambe of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.</note> which taketh away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the worlde.</p>
               <p>Wée are not redéemed with bryckle thinges,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.</note> as with corruptible ſiluer, and gold, but with the precious blood of Chriſt, as of a lambe vndefiled and without ſpot. Let theſe things enter into the bottome of thine heart, let theſe things lift thée vp, and giue thee comforte. There is no cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt doubt of the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, if thou conſtantly profeſſe the name
<pb facs="tcp:7028:13"/> of Chriſt, and truſteſt in his mercie, he will alſo take away thy ſinnes. If ſo be that thou nothing ſtick, nor ſtacker, but vndoubtedly beléeueſt this, nowe thou art become the ſonne of God, there is no cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt wauer, there is nothing that thou ſhouldeſt feare. Hearken vnto the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſcripture, but ſo hearken vnto them, that thou mayeſt ſurely print them in thy minde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note>So God loued the worlde, that he gaue his onely begotten ſonne, that none, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in him, ſhould periſhe, but ſhould haue euerlaſting lyfe. He that beléeueth on him, ſhall not be condemned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 9.</note>I came not to call the righteous, but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 11.</note>Come vnto mée all yee, that labour, and are laden, and I will refreſh you. He calleth all men vnto him, he refuſeth no man, he caſteth no man in the téeth. Thou art alſo comprehended in this worde, <hi>All.</hi> Call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his mercie, and he will comfort thée.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note>God ſetteth out his loue, that he hath to vs, ſéeing that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for vs. Much more then nowe, ſéeing that we are iuſtified in his blood,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7028:13"/> ſhall we be ſaued from wrath thorowe him. God the father, which earneſtly loueth thée, would y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this goſpell full of comfort, ſhoulde bée alſo declared vnto thée. For Chriſt was ſent vnto thée, and he alſo died for thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue onely, and commende thy ſelfe vnto Chriſt, thy preſeruer, and defender.</p>
               <p>If, when we were enimies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> we were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto God, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of his ſonne: muche more, ſéeing we are reconciled, wee ſhall be preſerued by his lyfe.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is made to vs wiſedome,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo righteouſneſſe, and ſanctifying, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>Here, déerely beloued brother, take a good hart, although thou bée neuer ſo great an offender, yet there is no matter, why thou ſhouldeſt deſpeire, but confeſſe, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thy ſelfe before Chriſt, to be a ſinner. Call vpon his mercie, and deſire pardon of him, aſke forgiueneſſe of thy ſinnes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that Chriſt is thy onely ſauiour, thy health, and iuſtification, and euer will be,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> he will both couer, and alſo aboliſhe all thy ſinnes, that thou ſhall neither feare perill nor dammage for them.</p>
               <p>God hath made him to bée ſinne for vs,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7028:14"/> which knew no ſinne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we, by his meanes, ſhould be that righteouſneſſe, which before God is allowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gala.</hi> 1.</note>Chriſt gaue himſelfe for our ſinnes, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer vs from this preſente euill worlde, through the will of God our father.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.</note>By Chriſt we haue redemption thorowe his blood, euen the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, according to the riches of his grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1.</note>Chriſt Ieſus came into the worlde, to ſaue ſinners.</p>
               <p>Haue thou a confidence in theſe wordes, and giue good credite vnto them, and thou ſhalt be iuſtified, and ſaued, as wel as ſaint Paule.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 2.</note>Chriſt Ieſus gaue himſelfe a ranſome for all men.</p>
               <p>Conſtantly beléeue this, and without all queſtion to the contrarie, thou art one of that number which ſhall be ſaued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.</note>We are ſanctified by the offering vp of the body of Ieſus Chriſt, once for all.</p>
               <p>Thou heareſt Chriſt alſo ſpeaking vnto thée, in his laſte ſupper, féeding thée with his body, and giuing himſelfe vnto thée ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, that thou mighteſt drink his blood, vnto euerlaſting lyfe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.</note> Where as he ſayeth:</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:7028:14"/>
               <p>Take eate this is my body,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> which is gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for you. This do in the remembrance of mée. And likewiſe when he had ſupped, he tooke the cup ſaying: This cup is the new teſtament in my blood, which is ſhedde for you, for the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. Doe this as often as yée ſhall drinke it, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of mée.</p>
               <p>Thinke thou, déerely beloued, that thoſe wordes were ſpoken vnto thée, faſten them in the bottome of thine heart. For when he ſpeaketh generally vnto al men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.</note> he ſpeaketh to thee alſo. All things which Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſhall doe thée good, they ſhall redownde vnto thine aduantage, and ſaluation, they ſhall profite thée, as much as they ſhall the déere ſaintes of God.</p>
               <p>Chriſt himſelfe bare our ſinnes in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, on the trée.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſinnes,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 3.</note> the iuſt for the vniuſt, for to bring vs to God.</p>
               <p>The blood of Ieſus Chriſte clenſeth vs from all ſinne.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If anye man ſinne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> we haue an aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the father, Ieſus Chriſt, which is righteous. He it is that abteyned grace for our ſinnes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7028:15"/>
               <p>Thou mayeſt take moe fewer or leſſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of ſcripture, for this purpoſe, euen as thou ſhalt perceyue the ſick to be affected.</p>
               <p>The words, which thou haſt now heard, are not the wordes of man, but of the holy Ghoſt, which plainly teſtifie, that God the father, whiche woulde not the death of a ſinner,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.</note> but that he might be conuerted and liue, for that his feruent loue, which he bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towardes thee, hath eaſed, and releaſed thée, from the burthen of thy ſinnes, &amp; hath layed them on the ſhoulders of his deerely beloued ſonne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> which hath ſo borne and ſuffered them all in his body: that they ſhal neuer be thy condemnation. For if ſo bée that thou beléeue in Chriſt, God reputeth, and accepteth the death of his ſonne, in the ſtead of a full and ſufficient repentance, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction, and abſolution for all thy ſinnes. Séeing therefore, thy ſinnes layed vpon Chriſt, coulde not deteyne, or kéepe him in death, and condemne him: ranſome is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly payd for them, and they are all fréely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen thée. Beléeue this, and thou ſhalt liue eternally. Chriſt himſelfe ſuffered for thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> &amp; died for them. But he roſe againe, and the ſinnes of all faithfull beléeuers, are
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7028:15"/> by his death acquited, purged, and clenſed, ſo that the ſtraight iuſtice, ſeuere iudgement of God, is aboundantly ſatiſfied through Chriſt. Nowe therefore Chriſt is become thine, and all others which beleeue, with al his benefites, with his death, with his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, with his aſſenſion into heauen, with his lyfe, with his merites, and with his glorie. Wherfore ſathan hath no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer thee at all, he can not hurte thée,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> ſéeing that thou art iuſtified through Chriſt, ſéeing that thou art deliuered from all thy ſinnes, ſéeing that thou art become the child of GOD. God is thy father, earneſtly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thée for Chiiſt his ſake, which hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled, and made a tonement for thée. Wherefore be thou of good courage, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce thou in the lorde. For ſéeing that thou art in the hands of almightie God, thy good and moſt faithfull father, thou art in ſafetie, and out of al daunger. For thou art encloſed and compaſſed about, with the cuſtodie of God, and garde of angelles. Chriſt is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither become thine, he couereth, and taketh awaye all thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10.</note> by his innocencie and righteouſneſſe. No man can by violence pluck thée out of the handes of thy heauenly
<pb facs="tcp:7028:16"/> father. Thou haſt now the victorie, when thou haſt ſuffered, and paſſed ouer this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall croſſe, &amp; affliction, the which being truely compared with eternall lyfe, ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere very eaſie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.</note> momentanie, &amp; but of a ſhort time. Chriſt was in the like agony, yea, in a farre more bitter, &amp; more horrible. He is gon before thée, he is thine head, to whom y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> muſt néedes become lyke, and die vnto ſinne, and muſt lay aſide this lyfe, ſpotted, and embru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with wickedneſſe, that thou mayeſt after lyue, the true life for euer, with thy mayſter Chriſt. Let not thy ſinnes, trouble thée. There is no cauſe, why thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ſhould be torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, ſéeing that thy ſinnes are now done away and aboliſhed. Thou haſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and haſt caſt vnder foote, that malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſpirite, which goeth about to worke the deſtruction of our ſoules. God now hath compaſſion on thée, he careth for thée, he doth defende, and kéepe thée, all the felowſhip of ſaintes, and aungels doe regarde thée. And euen as Chriſt can not be damned, ſo lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thou canſt not be damned, if ſo be that, thou beleue on him, with the full confidence of thine whole hart.</p>
               <p>If ſinne, death, and hell, can nothing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7028:16"/> hurt thy lorde, and mayſter Chriſt, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they hurt thée, for thou art miſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly graffed into Chriſt by fayth, and Chriſt is effectuall in thée, therefore thou canſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be damned. If ſo be that, thou thy ſelfe ſhouldſt beare thy ſinnes, and make a tone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for them, thou wouldſt by no meanes be able to ſuſteine and beare ſo great, and heauie a burthen, they woulde bee farre to weightie for thée, they woulde deuour thée, as one drowned into the bottome of hell.</p>
               <p>But Chriſt being perfite God, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite man, did offer himſelf vp of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord for thée, he did put himſelf in thy roume, diſcharging &amp; paying all things for thee, as it is written in the Pſalme:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.</note> I payde them the things, I neuer tooke. Truely thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt commit ſinne againſt thy ſelfe, but Chriſt purged them, and made ſatiſfaction for thée, and planted thée in libertie, if ſo be that thou beléeue this Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Although al the ſinnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, were layde vpon thée onely, yet, God hath grace and mercie ſufficient for them, &amp; more then ſufficient. God hath promiſed thée his grace, and bleſſing in Chriſt, and the ſame is ratified, certeine, full abſolute, and perfite
<pb facs="tcp:7028:17"/> in Chriſt thy lorde, and mayſter. Thou muſt néedes be ſaued, if ſo be that thou faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine eyes vpon Chriſt.<note place="margin">Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis.</note> For Chriſt is the naturall ſonne of God in diuine ſubſtance, veritie it ſelfe, and touching his humanitie, he is our fleſhe, and blood. Who will be more ſure, and certeine, then this Chriſt, to giue and perfourme the promiſe of grace, which is himſelfe the veritie of his promiſe, and loueth vs vnfaynedly, in ſomuch that, he had léefer dye, then to diſappoint vs in any parte of his promiſe. Wherefore if thou beleue in Chriſt, thou art now made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his heauenly bleſſing, thou art now eaſed of the burthen of thy ſinnes, nowe thou art the eire of God, and the fellowe eire with Chriſt for euer.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.</note> For heauen and earth ſhall paſſe, but the worde of the lorde endureth for euer. Therefore beléeue and ſtrengthen thy minde with good hope, and doubt not, but GOD is chéefeſt and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, yea, euen for thée, hee became man for thy ſaluation, he was alſo borne for thy ſake, hée dyed on the croſſe, he roſe from the deade, for thy ſake, and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into heauen, he offered vp, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all things, which were promiſed vnto
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7028:17"/> vs. For all the promiſes of God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> by Chriſt are yea: and are by him. Amen. Wherfore deſire of God, to haue his mercy, and then looke for none other thing at his hand, but méere grace, and mercy, and the ſame for Chriſt, and through Chriſt. For without him truely there is no conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no health, no hope, no helpe, or ſuccour. In this only Chriſt, is all comfort, all ayde, and ſtaye, and to be bréefe, all the meanes of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. In him is all grace and mercie, much more infinite, and greater, more highe, plentifull, and abundant, then anye man can either comprehend, or wyſhe for. God vouchſafe to graunt vs a ſure, and conſtant fayth.</p>
               <p>After this maner, thou ſhalt comfort the ſick body, either with longer, or ſhorter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as the matter ſhall require. And I admoniſh thée, déere brother in the lorde, that thou withdrawe thy minde, with as great endeuor, and ſtudie, as thou mayeſt, from the horrible contemplation of ſinne, and death, and bend all thy thoughts vpon Chriſt onely, faſten the eyes of thy minde vpon him, cleane vnto him with all thine hart, and as it were drinke him into thée,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:18"/> call vpon him with full truſt of minde, and commit thy ſelfe wholy vnto him. For thou ſhalt finde none other thing in this Chriſt, than excellent innocencie, righteouſneſſe, lyfe, and ſaluation, all the which, being deryued from Chriſt into thée, are now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thine, if ſo be that thou wilt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be thy redéemer, and authour of thy ſaluation. Wherefore I warne thée, &amp; doe oftentimes beate it into thée by repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that for good cauſe, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue not, or call to minde the remembraunce of thy ſinnes, nor torment thy ſelf by way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the multitude, and greatneſſe of them. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſinnes are baniſhed farre off from thée, ſet Chriſt crucified onely before thine eies, faſten him in thine hart, let thy whole minde, &amp; ſenſes be ſurely ſet on him, cleane faſt vnto him with all thine heart, neuer to be pulled away. By this meanes thou ſhalt withſtande, and preuaile againſt the gates of hell, be they neuer ſo cruell, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo horrible, and terrible. Call to minde with how great humanitie, and clemencie, with what gentleneſſe? &amp; benignitie Chriſt in the Euangelicall hiſtorie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 9.</note> hath receyued, and vſed all ſinners, which truely repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7028:18"/> haue aſked forgiueneſſe, and beſought his ayde, and mercy. And thou ſhalt finde Marie of Magdalene,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. <hi>Luc.</hi> 23. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.</note> thou ſhalt finde the theefe hanged on his right hande, thou ſhalt finde the publicane, <hi>Zachaeus,</hi> and many others, whom he receyued with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilous kindneſſe, &amp; pronounced them free from all their ſinnes, were they neuer ſo gréeuous. For Chriſt is verie grace it ſelfe, mercie, aide, conſolation, life, ioy, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all them which deſire thoſe things of him, and doe put their truſt, and confidence in him. God, which is veritie, and cannot lye, hath promiſed al theſe things for Chriſt his ſake vnto vs. He therefore will neuer deceiue vs, beguile vs, nor forſake vs.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, it will come into thy minde alſo, when thou art in daunger of death, if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haue hurted, or endammaged thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour by any meanes, as if thou eyther haue ſtollen, or taken away any thing from him, or if thou haue ſlaundered him. Here thou ſhalt doe euen the ſame thing, which Chriſt did, hanging vpon the Croſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.</note> thou ſhalt praye for all thine enimies, and ſhalt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them, from the bottome of thine hart, all the wrongs they haue done vnto thée. If
<pb facs="tcp:7028:19"/> any thing of thine be ſtolen from thée, thou ſhalt not violently requyre it agayne. If thou haue taken awaye anye other mans good, reſtore it againe if thou maye, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, that it may be reſtored againe, neyther ſhalt thou kéepe any thing priuie, but ſhalt confeſſe it vnto God, and aſke forgiueneſſe of the ſame, and be ſorie that thou haſt ſo offended. If ſo be that thou be not able for thy pouertie to repaie the thing thou haſt wrongfully taken, it ſhall bée ſufficient, if thou forgiue others, which haue done eyther wrong, or violence to thée in body, or goods, or haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away thy good name. If (I ſay) thou forgiue them with all thine hart, there is no cauſe, why thou ſhouldeſt be carefull. Be of good comfort, and doubt not, but God will forgiue thée, the wrongs which thou haſt done vnto others. Truely hée can not but releaſe his ſinnes, which forgiueth his neighbour. For he himſelfe hath taught vs this order, and way of recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</note> and looſing. If yée ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue other men there treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, your heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:7028:19"/>
               <head>Whether the ſick may lawfully ſeeke the phiſitions help, and vſe phiſick, or no.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſick body ſhall neyther deſpiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phiſition his help, nor haue it in admiration. Let his chéefe hope be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly faſtined vppon God, which as he alone did put the ſoule into the body: So he onely taketh it awaye, when it pleaſeth him. Sometime notwithſtanding, the phiſition is to bée ſent for, leaſt we ſhoulde ſéeme to tempt God. For ſéeing medicines of themſelues neither can reſtore health, nor cauſe diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet, notwithſtanding, when they are miniſtred of a naturall wiſe phiſition, well exerciſed in reaſonable rules, thei are whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and worthily called the handes of God, as <hi>Herophilus</hi> witneſſeth, the which thing alſo holye ſcripture teſtifieth. For it is written: Honor the phiſition.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 38.</note> For the moſt higheſt hath created him, for neceſſities ſake. The moſt higheſt hath created medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine out of the earth, and the prowdeſt man
<pb facs="tcp:7028:20"/> will not abhorre it. Tellers of deſtinies, inchauntours, wicked coniurers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuers, which pretende to cure the ſicke with falſe prayers, and oriſons, are to bée driuen awaye, and eſchued, as the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. For witches are the handes of the diuell, and not of almightie God, by whoſe worde, and power, all things ought to bée gouerned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>What is to be done, when death bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth terror, and feare vpon vs.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou ſhalt thinke that death is conquered, and vtterly deſtroyed by Chriſt. And except Chriſt hauing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on vs, had ſuffered death for vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of death woulde haue troubled vs, with great and horrible heauineſſe, and intolerable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of minde. But death béeing ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and deſtroyed by Chriſt, the ſoules of them, which truſt in him, can not dye and periſhe, but they go ſtraight wayes vnto Chriſt, after their departing out of this bodye. As the théefe béeing in extremitie
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7028:20"/> heard it ſayed vnto him:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.</note> This daye thou ſhalt be with me in paradiſe. The body in the meane ſeaſon reſteth in ſure hope, to riſe againe in the laſt daye, vnto that moſt bleſſed immortall lyfe, with great glorie, magnificence, and honour, as renewed, and clarified, that it may liue togither with the ſoule, for euer with Chriſt, and all his elect, amongſt whom we ſhall finde many, which were either our fréendes, or kinſfolks here in this worlde.<note place="margin">The death of godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is called a ſleepe.</note> Therefore holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calleth the death of godly men, a ſléepe. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verie ſame our brickle, fraile, weake, mortall, and corruptible body, ſhall be ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp in the laſt day, as a man ſtirred out of his ſléepe, and forthwith, death extinct, and aboliſhed, it ſhall appéere incorruptible, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, beautifull, ſounde, helthfull, immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, whole, pure, perfite, &amp; ſpirituall, as it is written vnto the Corinthians.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.</note> And hereof the pſalmiſt ſayeth: Right déere in the ſight of the lorde, is the death of his ſaints.</p>
               <p>Waighe thoſe things diligently in thy minde, déerely beloued, that thou mayeſt not be ſeduced with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked world, which ſuppoſeth vs vtterly to dye, the body togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſoule to decaye, and periſhe,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:21"/> and that no part of vs ſhall remayne, after the departing out of this lyfe. But they are farre out of the waye, and greatly deceyued therein. Our body is not ſo vile, and ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regarded in the ſight of God, but great honour, glorie, and ſaluation, is prepared and appointed for it. For the verie ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which we carie about with vs, and the ſame, which lyeth vpon the bedde afflicted, and tormented, the verie ſame body (I ſay) renewed, and glorified, ſhall liue togither with the ſoule for euer. If ſo bée that wée ſhoulde léeſe our body and neuer recouer it againe, the death of ſaintes were not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and honorable, but vile, horrible, and moſt cruell. Wherfore theſe things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red diligently, thou ſhalt ſupport, and holde vp thy wauering mind, erected by ſure hope in the ſentences of holy ſcripture. Beléeue them, and doubt nothing at all. For it is vndoutedly true that I tell thée. As the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt béeing buried, euen vntill the thirde daye, roſe againe the thirde day vnto a new and eternal life, neuer to die againe: ſo the bodies of all them, which haue ſlept in Chriſt, that is to ſay, which haue belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on Chriſt, doe reſt in there graues one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7028:21"/> for a time, to riſe againe in the laſt daye, in ſure hope of the moſt ioyful, and glorious reſurrection, into a new and perpetual life, where ſhall bée neyther ſinne, nor anye death, calamitie, or any other thing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> than righteouſneſſe, innocencie, lyfe, ioy, bliſful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſaluation worlde without ende. God, which is of infinite power, and veritie it ſelfe, hath promiſed thoſe things. They ſhall therefore come to paſſe vndoubtedly. Therefore truſt thou ſtedfaſtly vnto hys promiſes.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, the teſtimonies of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the reſurrection of the fleſhe, are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to be thought vpon, and earneſtly to be beaten into our mindes by often repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticion. Thus doth ſaint Paule teache vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> that we ſtrengthen one another with ſuch communication of the reſurrection, that we mought thereby be comforted. There can be none more certaine, nor more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conſolations giuen vnto vs, than thoſe which we ſeeke out of the teſtimonies of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſcripture, for the approbation of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. Wée declare not the wordes of man but of God, which ſurely, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily will performe, and bring to paſſe, all
<pb facs="tcp:7028:22"/> that he hath ſpoken. No man can alter the the will of God, no man can let, or hinder his purpoſe, and counſell. His power can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meaſured, he is true, and faithfull, his goodneſſe, and mercie is endleſſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let no man doubt thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The teſtimonies of ſcripture, for the reſurrection of the deade.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He iuſt men ſhall ſhine as bright, as the Sunne, in the kingdome of there Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5.</note>Verily, verily, I ſaye vnto you, hée that heereth my words, and beléeueth on him that ſent mée, hath euerlaſting lyfe, and ſhall not come into damnation, but is eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from death vnto lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6.</note>This is the will of him, that ſent me, that euery man which ſeeth the ſonne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth on him, haue euerlaſting lyfe, and I will rayſe him vp at the laſt day.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note>Verily, verily, I ſaye vnto you, if a man kéepe my ſayings, he ſhall neuer ſée death.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11.</note>Chriſt ſayde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lazarus did ſléepe, which notwithſtanding, had yéelded vp the ghoſt, whoſe deade body was committed vnto the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7028:22"/> graue. But Chriſt reſtoreth the dead vnto lyfe againe, and calleth thoſe things which be not, as though they were. Therefore he addeth this, ſaying: I am the reſurrection,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11.</note> and the lyfe. He that beléeueth on mée, yea though he were deade, yet ſhall lyue, and forthwith after thoſe wordes, hée rayſed vp Lazarus, which had layne foure daies in his graue, being putryfied, and ſmelling.</p>
               <p>And bicauſe we are fearefull, and faint-harted by nature in thoſe agonies: that we maye haue the better helpe to beléeue, that there ſhall be a Reſurrection, many were reſtored from death to lyfe, in the dayes of the prophets, and the apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Chriſt rayſed vp from death to lyfe the wydowes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He rayſed vp alſo the maiſter of the Sinagoge his daughter.<note place="margin">Iairus was hir father.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>He reſtored Lazarus vnto lyfe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11. <hi>Act.</hi> 9. <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 4.</note> Peter likewyſe made <hi>Tabytha</hi> aliue again.</p>
               <p>Paule reuiued <hi>Eutychus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Helyſeus the prophet reuiued his Hoſtes dead ſonne.</p>
               <p>Helias the prophet reuoked the womans childe of <hi>Sareptha</hi> to lyfe againe.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>God alſo aſſumed, and tooke vnto him,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:23"/> that two moſt holy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gene.</hi> 5. 4. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.</note> &amp; mighty men: <hi>Enoch,</hi> and <hi>Elia,</hi> rapt alyue both body, and ſoule togithers, out of this frayle, and wretched world, that he might by them giue vs ſome taſte, and ſignification of the true lyfe to come, leaſt we alſo ſhoulde beleue, that no parte of vs remayneth after this miſerable lyfe, according to the opinion of the heathen gentiles, and Epicures.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, the faint harted ſick body, is to be admoniſhed, that he remember, and thinke what that greateſt, and mightie lord both of lyfe, and death, Ieſus Chriſt ſayed in ſaint Luke his goſpell:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Iairus daughter.</note> Wéepe not, for the damſell is not deade, but ſléepeth. Mans reaſon harde of beléefe, not vnderſtanding the ſecrete myſteries of God, did laugh theſe wordes to ſcorne. But Chriſt making it true, verifying his words, reſtored the dead mayden vnto life againe, as ſoone as he had ſpoken the wordes. The very ſame lord Ieſus Chriſt, wil receiue thy ſoule, and will preſerue it, and in the laſt day he wil reſtore thy body vnto thy ſoule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, &amp; will couple them vnto eternall lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5.</note>The time ſhall come when al they, which are in there graues, ſhall heare the voice of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7028:23"/> the ſonne of God, and they that haue done good, ſhall come forth vnto the reſurrection of lyfe. If ſo be that the ſpirite of him, that rayſed vp Ieſus from death dwell in you, euen hée, that rayſed vp Chriſt from death,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> ſhall quicken your mortall bodies, bicauſe that his ſpirite dwelleth in you. God hath rayſed vp the lorde Chriſt, and ſhall rayſe vs vp by his power. The .xv.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> chapter of the firſt epiſtle to the corinthians, is full of moſt ſweete, and effectual conſolations hereof, no golde is to be compared vnto them. Saint Paule in the ſame chapter, ſo knitteth, and faſteneth our reſurrection vnto the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, that it maye not be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or ſeperated from it, as by this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Chriſt is riſen againe from the deade, the which thing is moſt certeine. Therefore without all doubt, wée alſo ſhall ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. For Chriſt is our heade,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 12.</note> and we are hys members myſtically. This head is not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out his members, neyther doth he leaue, and forſake his members. Where Chriſt is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.</note> there ſhall we be alſo. For we are members of his bodye, of his fleſhe, and of his bones. Who can ſufficiently declare, according to the worthyneſſe thereof, that vnmeaſurable
<pb facs="tcp:7028:24"/> glorie, of ineſtimable, &amp; vnſpeakable grace, and mercy, that God deſcending from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into the loweſt partes, did vouchſafe to become a mortall man, that this frayle, and bryckle nature of man, vnited vnto his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature, mought be brought vnto euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, being made partaker of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome, by the infinite, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible might, and efficacie of his diuinitie, and godhead. If we beléeue, that ſo great riches were beſtowed vpon vs, and that ſo bleſſed a lyfe remayneth for vs, how, I praye you, can we be falſe harted, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in minde? The nature of all faithfull people, which haue béene both before, and alſo ſince Chriſt, and thoſe which are yet to come, without all queſtion, hath put on im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie in Chriſt, being perfite God and perfite man. The comfort therfore of Chriſt his reſurrection, is moſt plentiful, and effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, wherewith ſaint Paule doth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the mindes of the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> where as he ſayeth: Chriſt is riſen from the deade, and is become the firſt fruites of them, that ſléepe. For by a man came death, and by a man came the reſurrection of the dead. For, as by Adam all dye, euen ſo by Chriſte,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7028:24"/> ſhall all be made alyue, and euery man in his own order. The firſt is Chriſt, than they that are Chriſts. Here ſaint Paule maketh a ſimilitude of naturall things, whereby the reſurrection maye be the more cléerely, and manifeſtly perceyued. And the ſimilitude is taken of drie ſeede, which the huſbandman caſteth into the earth. It dieth, &amp; rotteth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a faſhion. Yet notwithſtanding, that which is committed vnto the earth, doth not vtterly periſhe, but it commeth forth of the earth againe, freſhe, and new, with a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, hanſome, ioyful forme, and ſhape. And euen ſo ſhall our bodye riſe againe, not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, bryckle, fraile, feeble as now it is, but faire, cleane, beautifull, ſtrong, of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite force, and immortall vnto euerlaſting lyfe.</p>
               <p>This is the way by thys corporall death, vnto true, and eternall lyfe, into oure true countrey.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> Fleſh and blood cannot inherite the kingdome of God, wherein is nothing but lyfe, and therefore this mortalitie muſt put on immortalitie.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſac.</hi> 25. <hi>Oſeae.</hi> 13.</note> Then ſhall the ſaying come to paſſe, which is written: Death is ſwalowed vp into the victorie, they nowe whiche beléeue in Chriſt, haue ouercome
<pb facs="tcp:7028:25"/> ſinne, death, and hell. They therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning death, &amp; being ſtrong and bolde in Chriſt, will ſay: Hell where is thy victorie? Sinne is the ſting of death, the lawe is the ſtrength of ſinne. But prayſe be vnto God, which hath giuen vs the victorie, through our lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>We wyll adde alſo, other ſentences of ſcripture, conteyning plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull comfort.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that rayſed vp the lorde Ieſus Chriſt from death, ſhall rayſe vs vp alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phill.</hi> 3.</note>Our conuerſation is in heauen, from whence we looke for a ſauiour, euen the lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall chaunge our vile bodies, that they maye be faſhioned like vnto his glorious bodye, according to the working, whereby he is able to ſubdue all things vnto him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.</note>Yée are dead, and your lyfe is hidde with Chriſt in God. When Chriſt, which is our lyfe, ſhall ſhewe himſelfe, then ſhall ye alſo appéere with him in glorie.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:7028:25"/>
               <p>I woulde not, brethren,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> haue you igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant concerning them which are fallen a ſléepe, that ye ſorrow not, as other do, which haue no hope. For if we beléeue that Ieſus Chriſt dyed, and roſe againe: euen ſo they alſo which ſléepe by Ieſus, will God bring againe with him.</p>
               <p>And ſaint Paule doth comfort Tymothe his ſcholar in the articles of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by theſe wordes: Remember (ſayeth he) that Ieſus Chriſt, being of the ſéede of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, roſe againe from death,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo</hi> 3.2.</note> according to my goſpell. If we are dead with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo liue with him. If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall raigne with him.</p>
               <p>Saint Paule ſayeth, that Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.</note> by the grace of GOD, ſhould taſte of death for all men. And in the ſame place he ſayeth alſo, that Chriſt was made partaker of our fleſh, and blood, that is to ſaye, hée became perfite man, that hée might put downe through death, him that had lordſhip ouer death, that is to wit, the diuell, and that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer them, whoſoeuer through feare of death, were all there lyfe time in daunger of bondage.</p>
               <p>God ſaued vs,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 1.</note> and called vs with an holy
<pb facs="tcp:7028:26"/> calling, not according to our déedes, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne purpoſe, &amp; grace, which grace was giuen vs through Chriſt before the world was, but is now declared openly by the appéering of our ſauior Ieſu Chriſt, which hath put away death, &amp; hath brought lyfe, and immortalitie to light.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note>We know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are tranſlated from death vnto lyfe, bicauſe we loue the brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4.</note>In this appéered the loue of God to vs warde, bicauſe that God ſent his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten ſonne into the world, that we might liue thorow him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.</note>I am ſure that my redéemer lyueth, and that I ſhall ryſe out of the earth at the laſt day, and that I ſhall be clothed againe with this ſkin, and ſée God in my fleſhe, yea, I my ſelfe ſhall beholde him, not with other, but with the ſame eyes.</p>
               <p>He that diligently doth meditate &amp; thinke vpon theſe teſtimonies of ſcripture, cannot chooſe but take much comfort, and great ioy therof. Saint Paule may be a moſt euident example thereof vnto vs, which hartily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyſeth in his owne behalfe, that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phill.</hi> 3.</note> and the power of his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereby our death is ſlaine. Now therfore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7028:26"/> death is dead vnto all them, which beléeue in Chriſt, there is nothing now in death terrible, which is to be dreaded, and feared, beſides the onely ymage and ſhape thereof. Euen as a ſerpent being kylled, kéepeth notwithſtanding that his olde and fearefull figure, but hath no power in him to doe harme,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 21.</note> and euen as the lyue ſerpentes died, when the braſen ſerpent was looked on, which Moyſes ſet vp in the wilderneſſe, by the might of the power of God, and the Iewes could not be infected, with venome of the lyue ſerpentes: Likewiſe alſo our death his dead and made harmleſſe, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be feared, if we looke vpon and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the liuely death of Chriſt, wyth the eyes of our fayth. And to be ſhort, death is like the verie ymage and ſhadowe of death, yea, more rather ſhe is the beginning, and enteraunce into the true lyfe. Chriſt, which is the veritie it ſelfe, ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 24. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note> If a man kéepe my wordes, he ſhall neuer ſée death. How, I pray you, may this be? I will ſhowe you howe. A man, that truſteth in the mercie of Chriſt, by the fayth which he hath taken out of the goſpell, is ſo incorporated, as I may ſo terme it, and ſo vnited, and coupled vnto
<pb facs="tcp:7028:27"/> his lorde, and mayſter Chriſt, which is the true lyfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14.</note> that he may not be pulled or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from him. This body therefore is ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and deuided from the ſoule, in moſte ſure hope of the glorious reſurrection, vnto euerlaſting lyfe. For within ſhort ſpace, the body ſhal be reſtored againe vnto the ſoule, that they maye both enioy felicitie. And he that thus beléeueth in Chriſt, ſhall not ſée eternall death of body and ſoule, that is to witte, perpetuall damnation, which is the true death.<note place="margin">The death of godly men, is a going forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the company of the elect.</note> For the death of godlye men, is a going forth, and departing out of this mortall life, into immortalitie, vnto Chriſt, vnto the angelles, and vnto all the ſaints.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>What is to bee done, when hell, or eternall damnation, comming in our minds, doth feare vs.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He malignant ſpirite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth man verie ſolicitous, &amp; penſiue about his predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, putting thoſe cruell, and horrible thoughts of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination in hys mynde.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7028:27"/> What if thou ſhouldeſt not pleaſe God? What if he hath vtterly caſt thée off? How knoweſt thou, that thou art one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, whome God hath elected, and choſen vnto euerlaſting lyfe? Theſe, and the lyke temptations, are moſt bitter, and doe moſt gréeuouſly torment, and vexe the minde. Wherefore, thou muſt here ſtande faſt on both féete, as the prouerbe is, and it is needefull, that thou conſtantly defend thy ſelfe in this conflict. But it thou wouldeſt obtaine the victory in this battell, thou muſt ſet vpon him, by this policie, &amp; craft. Forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, as ſoone as theſe temptations come vnto thée from the Diuell, beware thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into diſputation with him, beware thou deale not with him, neyther anſwere him againe. But put him off from thée, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed awaye with theſe wordes, and cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Sathan get thée hence, depart vnto thy deſtruction. For it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 4.</note> Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lorde thy God. Séeing that God hath endued mée alwayes with moſt large, and infinite benefites, according to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue towardes me, ſeing that he hath giuen me this lyfe, and hath nouriſhed, and preſerued the ſame euen hitherto, ſeing that
<pb facs="tcp:7028:28"/> he hath heaped me vp, with all kind of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what madneſſe were it for mée, to doubt of his mercie? Seing that through baptiſme he hath appointed me into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to bée one of the receyued flocke of the chriſtians, ſeing that he hath called me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the goſpell of his grace, wherein he hath promiſed to be my father, why ſhoulde I not then looke for all goodneſſe at his hands? Why ſhould I not aſſure my ſelfe of him in all things? Wherfore ſhould not his great good will, and kindneſſe towardes mée, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be remembred of mée, for my ſtay, and comfort? What néede many words? It is a moſt fooliſhe, &amp; perillous thing, to yeelde our minds, &amp; ſtudie to ſuch cogitations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning predeſtination, but forthwith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, &amp; preuent thou ſuch cogitations, with others, wherwith god would haue thy mind to be occupied, &amp; preuented, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wit, with thoſe, which Chriſt himſelfe hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3.</note> where as he ſayeth: He, that beleeueth in Chriſt, ſhall not periſhe, but ſhall haue euerlaſting life.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> Heareſt thou, that he, which beléeueth in Chriſt, which acknowledgeth Chriſt to bee his ſanctification, ſaluation, and iuſtification, cannot be damned, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7028:28"/> that he ſhall bée partaker of eternall lyfe? How many ſoeuer therof doe truſt vnto the mercie of Chriſt, without all doubt, they be of the number of them, which are choſen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lyfe euerlaſting, being foreknowne and fore ordayned in Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.</note> now already writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of lyfe. And thoſe which are predeſtinate vnto eternall lyfe, are made and become, like vnto the ymage of Chriſt. For they conceyue there fayth, for the which they are counted to bée iuſt before God, of none other thing, but of the worde of God. They are ſaued therfore, by this faith,<note place="margin">The iuſt man ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by faith. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. <hi>Abac.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.</note> that is to ſaye, by the truſt and hope of mercie, fréely giuen vs for Chriſt his ſake. Thoſe things are moſt certeine and true. God can neyther be deceyued, nor deceyue any man. This is the purpoſe, and intent of God, our moſt bountifull father, and the true louer of mankinde. He from the beginning hath ſo purpoſed, ſo foreknowne, ſo before determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thoſe things. There is no cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that thou ſhouldeſt be letted, or feared with thoſe things, which that enimie enuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſaluation, and pretending the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our ſoules, putteth in thy minde and layeth againſt thée. Sée onely that thou
<pb facs="tcp:7028:29"/> beléeuing in Chriſt, doe comfort thy ſelfe, in the confidence of his mercie, and there ſhall be no perill at all. For if thou faſten thy hope,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> &amp; truſt on Chriſt, Chriſt is made thine, and thou art Chriſtes. If he haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemed thée, thou canſt by no meanes bée damned, and periſhe. For he that beléeueth on Chriſt, is drawen vnto him by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10.</note> and he will haue them to be ſaued by him, &amp; none of them to periſh. Wherfore, ſée that thou haue a good hart, ſée that thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue conſtantly on Chriſt, and conceyue ſure hope of him. How many ſoeuer beleue on Chriſt, the ſame are predeſtinate vnto euerlaſting lyfe. We muſt therefore, faſten our eyes vpon Chriſt, we muſt flye vnto him. This our onely, and true ſauiour, is to be taken holde on by faith, if we intende to be ſaued. Here let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diligently way, that earneſt exhortation of ſaint Paule, whoſe words are theſe: Let vs runne with pacience vnto the battell, that is ſet before vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.</note> looking vnto Ieſus, the author, and the finiſher of our fayth, which for the ioy, that was ſet before him, abode the croſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet downe on the right hande of the throne of God.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:7028:29"/>
               <p>Furthermore, Chriſt for vs, and for our ſakes ſuffered all temptations, with the which, being moſt gréeuous, he was vexed, and troubled, the ſame ſaint Paule bearing witneſſe thereof ſaying:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.</note> We haue not an high prieſt, which can not haue compaſſion of our infirmities, but was in all pointes tempted lyke as we are, but yet withoute ſinne. Let vs therefore, go boldly vnto the ſeate of grace, that we may receyue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in tyme of néede. Print thoſe things, déerely beloued, in thy minde. Firſt, Chriſt was giuen vnto vs for this purpoſe, that he might redéeme vs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile vs, and make vs partakers of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſaluation. Secondly, that he might be an example vnto vs, to leade, and paſſe ouer a godly life. Therfore if ſo be that thou deſire to finiſh thy life wel, and vertuouſly, ſée that the death of Chriſt, being ſet before thine eyes, thou ende thy lyfe after his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. For Chriſt is ſet before vs, as a patterne to be folowed of vs, in our lyfe, and conuerſation, in all afflictions, and in our death. No man lyueth godly, no man ſuffereth aduerſitie, no man dyeth well, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he ſet before him the lyfe, and death of
<pb facs="tcp:7028:30"/> Chriſt, and doe folow the ſame. The death of all godly men, is aboliſhed, &amp; ſwalowed vp in the death of Chriſt. Wherfore, thou ſhalt conſider, &amp; diligently meditate, what kinde of death he ſuffered, how he behaued himſelfe in that agonies of all other moſte bitter, when he hanging on the croſſe, was troubled, and peſtered with moſt gréeuous temptations. Folow this Chriſt, as neere as thou mayeſt, calling for helpe at Gods handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Howe chriſt was tempted on the croſſe. <hi>Mark.</hi> 15. <hi>Math.</hi> 27. <hi>Luc.</hi> 23.</note>Firſt, he was tempted with death, when as it was ſayd vnto him: He ſaueth others, but himſelfe he cannot ſaue. As though they ſhould ſaye. Now he is vndone, he muſt die, and periſhe for euer, no man ſhall delyuer him, and pluck him out of our hands. After this manner, that our olde, and mortall enimie will bring the terrour of death on thée. But ſo muche the bolder go thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, pluck vp thine hart, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thee in him with a ſure hope. Chriſt will ſubdue, and tread vnder foote, that eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and thou alſo ſhalt ouercome him by Chriſt. Hold vp the ſhield of faith in Chriſt. Chriſt is the lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 5.</note> he is the king of glorie, and he is the lorde of lyfe, he is not ſubiect
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7028:30"/> to death, but liueth and reigneth.</p>
               <p>This thy lorde, and reuenger, will not ſuffer death to exerciſe hir tirannie vpon thée. He cannot deceyue thée, neyther can he lye, ſeing that he is the veritie it ſelfe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue thou this truſt, and confidence of him. Aſſure thy ſelfe, to receyue all goodneſſe at his hands, and thou ſhalt lyue with him for euer. And for that he woulde haue the gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with temptations, and to ſuffer death of bodye, it is done onely for thy commoditie. Thou muſt therefore leaue and forſake this lyfe, if thou wilt enioy euerlaſting lyfe. So after this lyfe, thou ſhalt in the ende begin to lyue in deede. Furthermore, this corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall death, profiteth thée to this purpoſe, that when thou haſt taſted the bitterneſſe, and ſharpneſſe therof, thou mayeſt trie, &amp; know, how feruent the affection of Chriſt his loue was towardes thée, what an vneſtimable benefite hée beſtowed vpon thée, that he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for thée, did paye, and make ſatiſfaction with his bodye for all thine offences, death throughly extinguiſhed, and aboliſhed, and the gates of hell throwne downe, deſtroyed, and alſo broken. For thou couldeſt neuer any other wayes know, and vnderſtand the
<pb facs="tcp:7028:31"/> ſtrength, and power of life in Chriſt, which hath ſwalowed vp our death, thou ſhouldſt not know the largeneſſe of his benifits nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhouldeſt thou be able to giue ſo harty thankes to Chriſt, thy lorde and redéemer. Wherfore, ſeing that Chriſt doth liue, thou alſo ſhall lyue by him, and this ſame death ſhal be vnto thée a certeine, happy, &amp; whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſléepe. It ſhall be alſo an entrance, and gate into that true, and moſt bleſſed lyfe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Chriſt was alſo tempted with ſinne, when they did reuile, and vpbraide him, as a verie wicked man, and giltie of moſt gréeuous crime.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 27.</note> If thou be the ſonne of God, come downe from the croſſe. Thou ſaueſt others, why doeſt thou not ſaue thy ſelfe alſo? What other thing meane theſe contumelious wordes, then that they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and thought, that he deceiued the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by fraude, dole, ſlight, wiles, noughtie craftineſſe, and that he was not in déede the ſonne of God, yea, they iudged him rather to be moſt wicked, moſt abhominable, and moſt worthy of reproch. Euen likewiſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than will tempt man, being in daunger of death, he will preſent vnto him, whatſoeuer he hath done, and committed againſt the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7028:31"/> commaundement of God, and will put into his minde, whole waynlodes, as it were, of ſinnes, the ſame heaped vp, into a great abundance, that by the outragiouſneſſe, and greatneſſe of ſinnes, he maye bring man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſperation, which ſtaggereth, and doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of Gods mercie, and pardon. And here thou muſt ſtand faſt, and ſtrongly, and ſhalt enterteine thine enimy aſſaulting thée, with theſe wordes: I confeſſe that I am a moſt manifold, and gréeuous ſinner. But Chriſt frée from all ſinne, he, that innocent lambe, in whoſe mouth was founde no guile,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2.</note> hath ſuffered cruell death for my ſinnes, he hath clenſed them all, be they neuer ſo great, nor neuer ſo many, and hath made ſufficient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for them all. Chriſt his death, is the propitiation for al my ſinnes.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> Chriſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily hath ſuffered all my féebleneſſe. He in déede hath caried all my ſorowes. He was wounded for mine iniquities.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> He was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for my ſinnes. By his woundes am I healed. He hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, al my ſinnes, I now acknowledge none, I thank Chriſt, which hath payed ranſome for them all.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he was alſo tempted with hell, or eternall damnation, when they obiected
<pb facs="tcp:7028:32"/> againſt him, ſaying: He hath truſted in the Lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 27.</note> let him take him, let him ſaue him, bicauſe he will haue him, as thoughe they ſhould ſay: All his hope in God ſhal deceyue him. God is his aduerſarie, and abhorreth him, and will caſt him awaye for euer, as one thruſt downe into hell. When the ſame tempter prouoketh thée w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch lyke temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, take héede thou ſtand faſt. There is no cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt feare, there is no cauſe, why thou ſhouldeſt tremble. Let the thing, which he offereth, and preſenteth vnto thée, nothing moue thée at all, bée it neuer ſo gréeuous. Put out of thy minde, and baniſh awaye farre from thee, as well ſinne, as death, and hell. They haue no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer thée, if thou faſten thine eies vpon Chriſt. Take holde on him, and commend thy ſelfe wholy vnto him. Chriſt is thine, and he beſtoweth himſelfe wholy vpon thée. He hath redéemed thée from the tirannie of the diuell, and euerlaſting damnation by an ineſtimable price. This Chriſt is thine innocencie, thy lyfe, and thy righteouſneſſe. Take héede onely that thine hart be neuer withdrawne from Chriſt crucified, by any temptations. If thou cleaue faſt vnto thys
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7028:32"/> Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt be ſafe, againſt all the gates of hell, as one that is placed vpon an high, moſt ſure, and inuincible rocke, that thou mayeſt crie out with Chriſt:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.</note> I haue ſet God alwaies before me. He is on my right hand. Therfore I ſhal not fal. Wherfore my hart was glad, and my glorie reioyſed, my fleſhe alſo ſhall reſt in hope. Thou haſt ſhewed me the pathes of lyfe. In thy preſence is the fulneſſe of ioye, and at thy right hande is pleaſure for euermore. Thou art become, through ſuch a faith in Chriſt, the childe of God, the brother, and felow eire w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.</note> and partaker of eternall lyfe. This fayth iuſtifieth the righteous, that is to ſaye thoſe, which beleue in Chriſt. For this faith, thou ſhalt be reputed the bleſſed child of God, thy heauenly father, and when thou depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt hence, thou ſhalt enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> prepared for the elect chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of GOD, from the beginning of the worlde.</p>
               <p>But if ſo be that thy fayth wauer, and be doubtfull in temptations, and when thou doeſt not ſuffer moderately, and paciently ynough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of thy heauenly father, when thy loue towardes God is ſomewhat colde,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:33"/> when thy hope is weake, and ſlender, and for this cauſe feareſt, leſt thou ſhouldeſt not well accorde with God, or leſt he will be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with thée. Truely, this is a moſt gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, moſt painefull, and hard temptation. But thou ſhalt thinke in thy minde, and perſwade with thy ſelfe, that Chriſt ſuffered for thée moſte intolerable,<note place="margin">Inuinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing mere ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood.</note> and inuincible temptations, wherein there appéered no helpe, comfort, ayde, or defence, any where, wherein God, and the whole world ſéemed to be his moſt cruell, &amp; malycious enimies, when that he cryed aloude: My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</p>
               <p>Oh horrible, and moſt cruell temptation, oh good God, how ſharpe, how greeuous, how cruel, how bitter was the death, which he ſuffered for vs, that he might make the way of the croſſe eaſie for vs. Therefore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Chriſt willingly put himſelfe in ſubiection, and dipped himſelfe in thoſe ſo horrible, and intolerable ſorrowes, and calamities, our moſt louing heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wylling the ſame, out of doubt, he alſo vnderſtandeth, and knoweth our infirmity, out of doubt, he taking compaſſion on vs, will not extréemely deale with vs, but will
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7028:33"/> rather beare with our imbecilitie, &amp; weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Doth not he himſelfe calling all men vnto him ſay: Come vnto me,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 11.</note> al ye that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, and are heauie laden, and I wil refreſh you? what more plentifull, what greater comfort, I pray you, can be giuen vs? Truly many, &amp; very gréeuous things, do moleſt, &amp; trouble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For what thing can more grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly feare, what thing can more cruelly vexe, and torment his conſcience, ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with ſinne, then when he doubteth of the mercie of God, when he dreadeth leaſt God be his aduerſarie, and will reiect him, when he is not able to conceyue this fayth of his mercie, and doth imagine himſelfe to be caſt awaye, as a drie member that is cut off? Be preſent here O Ieſus Chriſt, with thine aide and helpe, here we haue néede of thy comfort, let not this black, violent, and horrible tempeſt of troubles ouerthrowe, and drowne wretched man. But there is no cauſe why we ſhoulde doubt. Chriſt is true, he will make his promiſes to appéere, he will helpe vs, and refreſhe vs. Therfore, where as thy fayth is not ſtrong ynough, where as thy hart is ſtriken with feare, and trembling, where as thou féeleſt thy ſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:7028:34"/> doubt of Gods mercie, and haſt well néere no faith at all: ſtraight wayes call vppon God, bewayle thy miſerie, and lack of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe before him, ſeeke for his ayde and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour by feruent prayer, and hée will both helpe and refreſhe thée, and by this meanes thou ſhalt glorifie him. He hath taken vpon him thus to do, and he will bring it to paſſe. But take héede eſpecially thou ceaſe not to call vpon God.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> Beſéech thou, without all ceaſſing, the father of all conſolation, and comfort, with ſighes comming from the bottome of thine hart, that he turne not his face from thée. Laye thy weakeneſſe vpon him, and poure out into his boſome al other things, which trouble, and torment thée. Crie out with his diſciples,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 17. <hi>Math.</hi> 9.</note> O lord increaſe my faith. Lykewiſe, ſay thou with the father of the lunatike childe: Lorde I beleue, help thou mine vnbeléefe. Make haſt O lorde to helpe me, before that I, oppreſſed with this weight, be drowned. Thy mercie is aboue all thy workes, O moſt mercifull, O moſt bounteous father, O lorde God of my ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.</note> my ſuccour, and refuge, enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant. Chriſt is my righteouſneſſe, redemption, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7028:34"/> which ſuffered moſt bitter, and cruel death for my ſake. Let thoſe things moue thée O father of all compaſſion. Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on me, for this thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſake. Confirme and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine hart, by faith in Chriſt. Comfort mée with the conſolations of the holy ghoſt, that I may enioy the true ioyes in Chriſt for euer.</p>
               <p>If thou after this maner laboring, ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and fighting with thine imbecillitie, and weakeneſſe, accuſing, and bewayling thine incredulitie, and faint courage, doe take holde vpon Chriſt, and ſticke faſt and ſure vnto him once taken, deſiring, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeching his ayde with continuall and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will vouchſafe to fulfill all things lacking in thée, ſubſtituting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in thy roume, if (I ſay) y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> thus doe, then all ſhall be in good caſe, all things ſhall go well with thee, and there ſhall be no perill. For truely theſe two things, to beléeue in Chriſt, and to cal for faith by earneſt praier, doe not much differ one from the other. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou be weake, and endued with a féeble minde, let this thing notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding comfort, and aduaunce thée againe, that God hath commaunded, and wylleth
<pb facs="tcp:7028:35"/> that we ſhoulde call vpon him, and that he hath promiſed to héere beneuolently,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.</note> and to helpe vs when we call vpon him. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, as nothing is more iuſtly deſired of God, than true fayth: euen ſo he héereth no prayer ſooner, &amp; more wyllingly, than that wherein man finding no goodneſſe in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, acknowledging his infirmitie, hys weakeneſſe, and miſerie, accuſeth his vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe, bewayling, and lamenting the ſame, deſiring to haue faith with plentie, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſighes, &amp; earneſt prayers. Theſe ſighes, theſe prayers, this ſmale faith, be it neuer ſo little, is in déede a godly, and a bright ſparkle, and the ſéede of God, which neuer riſeth, without the efficacie, and working of God in vs, which ſpeaketh of Chriſt, by the prophet Eſay:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 42.</note> A bruſed réede ſhall hée not breake, and the ſmoking flaxe, he ſhall not quench. Wherefore ſee that thou beleue conſtantly on Chriſt, or beſéeche him at the leaſt wiſe with hartie prayers, that thou mayeſt beleeue, bewayling thine vnbeléefe, before God. If thou doe thoſe things, thou ſhalt nothing doubt, but thou art reckened righteous before God, and to be his childe, which not without conſideration, nor in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7028:35"/> vaine, did laye our weakeneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 53.</note> and all our ſinnes vppon Chriſt, his onely begotten ſonne.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</note> Chriſt himſelfe ſayeth in ſaint Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew: Bleſſed are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pore in ſpirit. For theirs is the kingdome of heauen. Bleſſed are they that mourne. For they ſhal receiue comfort. Bleſſed are they which hunger, and thirſt after righteouſneſſe. For they ſhall be filled. Theſe wordes were ſpoken vnto thée alſo, they doe well agrée, &amp; accorde in thée. Thou doeſt mourne, and art ſorie for thy wicked lyfe, it gréeueth thée from the bottome of thine hart, thou doeſt thirſt, and hunger af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſſe, haue a good hope, and be of good comfort, and thou ſhalt obtaine the things, which thou doeſt deſire, and nowe thou art reputed iuſt before God through Chriſt. For that cauſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> thou ſhalt commit thy ſoule into the hande of God the father, after the example of Chriſt, and ſaint Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan ſaying theſe wordes:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acto.</hi> 7.</note> O moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father, I giue, and commit into thine handes my ſpirite, yea, rather thy ſpirite, ſeing that thou haſt giuen it me, ioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my body for a ſeaſon, ſeing that it is thine owne ymage, &amp; lykeneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 2.</note> made after thine owne ſimilitude, ſeing that thine onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten
<pb facs="tcp:7028:36"/> ſonne did ſhed his moſte precious blood, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redemption thereof. O moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable father, O God of all mercie, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, I eftſoones commend this my ſpirit into thine handes. I am thine, whatſoeuer I am. Receiue thine, I beſéech thée, preſerue him, and giue him eternall life through our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, thine onely begotten ſonne. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the making of a teſtament, and confeſſion of ſinnes vnto God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He teſtament is to be made of all them, that may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully make a will, and giue legacies, when there yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth and remayneth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite minde, and memorie in the body. Leaſt if they prolong that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto the laſt moment of lyfe, they bée preuented by death. Therfore, it ſhal be wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for him, that hath lawfull heires, to referre all the care of making his teſtament vnto them. If ſo be that he haue borowed money, and be indebted to any man, he ſhall
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7028:36"/> openly declare it, and prouide for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that he oweth. This being done, let him remoue and put from him all them, which trouble hym wyth matters of this worlde. Wherein many men doe offende, which bring in doubtes vnto him, which is now at the point of death, of his teſtament, and other externall things, and ſometimes doe compell him to ſubſcribe, &amp; that againſt his will, being readie to dye, refuſing, and deteſting there importunitie, which will not ſuffer him quietly to die, then the which fréends, what thing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be more vnfreendly?</p>
               <p>After this, if the maner, and kinde of his diſeaſe will ſuffer him, let him endeuor ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to cure his ſoule, than his bodye, by a ſhorte confeſſion vnto God, but ſimple, and without diſſimulation, and let the elders ſtanding by, put him in remembrance of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce, grounded vpon a ſure faith, and deuotion, and let him call for Gods mercie from the bottome of his hart, and purpoſe, and entende the amendement of lyfe, if hée happen to eſcape. But if ſo be that happily no elder, or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell giuer may be had, let not the ſick ſtraight waies fal into deſperation, as ſome preſumptuous people are woont to
<pb facs="tcp:7028:37"/> doe for the lacke of a prieſt, but let him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his vnrighteouſneſſe, and open his conſcience vnfainedly vnto God himſelfe, which according to his cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, wil vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, to accept the deſire of the minde, in the ſteade of the fact, and will of his peculiar grace, fulfill of himſelfe that, which lacketh in the outwarde ſignes of the ſacraments of the Lordes ſupper, which he deſireth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue. For through him, the ſacramentes are made effectuall, which after a faſhion are ſeales of his diuine beneuole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towards vs.<note place="margin">The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are ſeales of Gods mercye towardes vs.</note> But he ſaueth man, when néede doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, without theſe ſignes, onely ſo that there be no neglecting, or contempt of the ſacrament, but faith, and a readie good will is therevnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Of the ſacrament of the lords ſupper.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et the ſicke body earneſtlye deſire to haue the moſt royal ſacrament of thanks giuing to bée brought,<note place="margin">Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtia.</note> and miniſtred vnto him, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his minde is purged by a true, and a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7028:37"/> perfite confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, made vnto almighty God, as is aforeſaide, and let him eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, that he come not to that banquet, or heauenly table with iniurous handes, and ſpotted conſcience. For we may not thinke, that thoſe gréeuous threatnings are vaine, and of none effect,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> which ſaint Paule ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention off. Therefore after that hee hath examined, and prepared himſelfe for that purpoſe, according to his power, and capacity, let him deuoutly record and ſpeake theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>O lorde thou art the wayfaring cottage of our pilgramage,<note place="margin">A prayer.</note> wherewith we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, and nouriſhed, as long as we hoſt in the deſerte of this worlde, and runne in this courſe. Bring mée therefore, O lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.</note> into the lande of the lyuing, into the region of the quick, by the receyuing of this thy body, whereas I may beholde thée face to face, in the glory of the father. When we haue thus prayed, let him with a ſure fayth, receyue the ſacrament of Chriſt his body, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his death, and paſſion.</p>
               <p>And when the communion is ended, if it be perceiued, that no ſkil of phiſick may cure his diſeaſe, then let the elders pray ouer the
<pb facs="tcp:7028:38"/> ſick body,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5.</note> not vſing any magicall prayers, as the heathen were woont to doe, but ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly calling vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Ieſus Chriſt, wherevnto there is no kinde of inchaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comparable, or lyke effectuall, and ſée that he haue a confidence and affiance in your prayers, then will God héere you, and preſerue him that is ſicke, and he ſhall not onely haue the health of his body, reſtored vnto him againe, if it ſo be good, &amp; expedient for him:<note place="margin">Bodily ſickneſſe do ſpring out of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of the minde.</note> but if he haue happily committed ſinne, as commonly the ſickeneſſe of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doe ſpring out of the enormyties, and naughtineſſe of the minde, they ſhall be forgiuen him, at the prayers of the elders, if that both they, which praye, and he for whom they do pray, bée of a ſtedfaſt and conſtant fayth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7028:38"/>
               <head>The ſorow which many take, more then is requiſite for the death of there pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, and friends, ought to be tempered by the right rule of reaſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the parte of an heathen gentile, rather than of a chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian man, to giue himſelfe onely vnto teares, refuſing all temperance, and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of reaſon in ſorowing, the which thing is conuinced, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye reproued by thys reaſon eſpecially, bicauſe that they, which are ſorowed for, cannot be reuoked, and called backe againe vnto lyfe by wéeping, be it neuer ſo much, or neuer ſo long continued, and vſed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe teares are vaine, and of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, bringing no fruite or commoditie with them.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 12.</note> The which thing king Dauid hath declared vnto vs, by an example, worthie of memory, which faſted, and wept abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. As long as the childe, borne vnto him of <hi>Berſabe</hi> was ſicke, and languiſhed, he gat himſelfe alone, and lay flat on the grounde,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:39"/> praying vnto the lorde, for the health of the childe. But as ſoone as he vnderſtoode by his ſeruauntes, which whiſpered togithers, that the childe was deade, he caſteth off his ſadde, and mourning garmentes, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parelled himſelfe in freſhe aray, hée waſhed his face, and when the table was layed, he did eate chéerefully. Whereat his ſeruants marueyled, and thought, that when hée had vnderſtoode of his childes death, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would the more afflict himſelfe, which, whileſt the childe was yet lyuing, did pine himſelfe, with faſting, and weeping. He ſaid vnto his ſeruantes, demaunding why he did ſo. I haue faſted, and wept for the infant, whyle he yet lyued. For I ſaid: Who can tell if the lorde peraduenture will giue me the infant, that he may liue? But now, ſeing that he is dead, wherefore ſhould I faſt? What, can I call him againe? I ſhal rather go vnto him, then he ſhall reuerte and come againe vnto mée. By the which wordes truely, Dauid wiſely declared, that we ought not to lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and ſorrow for him, which cannot be reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and called back againe vnto lyfe.</p>
               <p>¶This ſermon of ſaint Cyprian, is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die tranſlated into engliſh, by the famous
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7028:39"/> learned, and worſhipfull knight, ſir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Eliote. Wherefore I did ommit the ſame, leaſt happily the prouerbe ſhoulde be verified on mee: <hi>Cornicum oculos configere,</hi> to endeuor to prick out the crowes eyes. And ſaint Cyprian in his ſermond entituled of mortalitie teſtifieth, that he was often ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by diuine reuelation, wherin God commaunded him, that he ſhoulde openly warne all men, and ſhould teache them by preaching, that the breathren which depart out of this worlde by Gods calling, ought not to be lamented, and that ſuch wayling is lothſome and hated of God.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding, it is méete that we ſhould ſometime participate our teares, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a naturall zeale of the minde, and the ſyncere affect of compaſſion, but mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by the right rule of reaſon, leaſt we ſhould ſéeme to haue an hart as hard as an adamant ſtone, &amp; to haue looued our fréend little, or nothing at al. For Chriſt our lord, the abſolute, &amp; perfite figure of all vertues, louingly lamented dead Lazarus. And Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and Martha, were highly commended, for that they lamented their brothers buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. And thoſe fréendly women,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11.</note> which dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb facs="tcp:7028:40"/> ſtoode by Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 23. <hi>Math.</hi> 27.</note> when he ſuffered his paſſion vpon the croſſe, were therefore worthily praiſed, bicauſe they wept for him, when he was deade and buried. We reade alſo in the actes of the apoſtles,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acto.</hi> 7.</note> of S. Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, the firſt martyr, that godly men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for him all that appertained vnto the funerall of his buriall. Yea, and further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> doth admoniſh vs, to wéepe for the deade, but not immoderately, or any long time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 22.</note> ſaying thus: Wéepe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him that is deade, bicauſe the light fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth him. Make but little wéeping for the deade, bicauſe he is come to reſt. Alſo verye many epiſtles of the holy father ſaint Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome, comforting vs vpon the death of our fréendes, are of great efficacie for the ſame purpoſe, whereof I now entreate. For they perſwade by the authority of holy ſcripture, &amp; ſtrong reaſons, that they ought not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderately to be lamented, which chaunge their life with death. As that epiſtle which he wrote vnto <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> vpon the death of <hi>Nepotianus,</hi> that, which he wrote vnto <hi>Paula</hi> vpon the death of hir daughter <hi>Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilla,</hi> and that, which he wrote vnto <hi>Tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> of the death of his daughter, and the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7028:40"/> reſt of that moſt reuerende father his epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, touching the like matter &amp; argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>A precept containing an exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto all them, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the name of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Now humbly deſire,<note place="margin">Parae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis.</note> &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily beſéech you, by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, as manie as are called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that once in the ende, yée forſake your olde darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and horrible errors, and returne vnto better proofe of lyfe, and to harken vnto the wholeſome receiued worde of God, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great deſire of a pure hart, and deuotion, knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without ceaſing, and that ye call vpon the father of heauen through Chriſt, that he wil inſtruct vs, and lighten vs with the true knowledge of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.</note> that we may liue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly, righteouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent lyfe, refuſing the wickedneſſe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence of the worlde, looking for that bleſſed hope, and appéerance of the glorie of almightie God, &amp; Ieſu Chriſt our ſauiour, which gaue himſelfe for vs, that he might
<pb facs="tcp:7028:41"/> redéeme vs from all our iniquities,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2.</note> &amp; clenſe vs to be a peculiar people vnto himſelf, and folowers of good workes.</p>
               <p>That worde of grace, light, and all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, hath ſhyned vnto vs, by the excéeding benefite of God. We haue verie many no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table examples in holy ſcripture, teſtifying the abundant goodneſſe, long ſuffering, and clemencie of God towards vs, whereby we maye eaſily perceyue, how that hée woulde not haue vs to be caſt awaye,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>EZech.</hi> 18.</note> but that we ſhould be conuerted and lyue, how ſoone his wrath, be it neuer ſo iuſt, waxeth colde, how ſoone be letteth paſſe the puniſhment, which we deſerue, when we thinke on the amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our lyfe, earneſtly repenting. Let vs alſo, déerely beloued, flye vnto God in all our afflictions, being moued therevnto by theſe things. Let vs deſire him with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall prayers, that he will vouchſafe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully to forgiue vs all our ſinnes, for that his welbeloued ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, and that he will vouchſafe to preſerue, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, defend, and comfort vs, and to be briefe, he will vouchſafe to be our preſent aide, and ſuccour in all neceſſities.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.</note>As ſoone as Dauid, being caſt into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7028:41"/> perill, when there died thrée ſcore and ten thouſande, within fewe dayes, by the fierceneſſe of the peſtilence, did flye vnto God, confeſſing his ſinnes, deſiring pardon for them, earneſtly calling vpon the mercy of God, &amp; building an aulter in the threſhing floure of Arefnath the Iebuſite, and offered vp burnt ſacrifice, and peace offerings, God tooke compaſſion on the lande, &amp; the plague ceaſſed from Iſraell. After this example call you alſo vpon the grace and mercie of God, confeſſing your ſinnes, offering vp vnto God an acceptable ſacrifice of a penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and contrite hart, and he will be preſent with you, and helpe you, and will neuer forſake you.</p>
               <p>Likewyſe God ſent the prophet Ionas,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ionas.</hi> 3.</note> and threatened to ouerthrow, &amp; deſtroy that moſte famous, and populous citie Niniue. But as ſoone as the Niniuites did repent at the preaching of Ionas, GOD tooke mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on them, forgaue their offences, and did withholde his puniſhment. Follow their example, and miſtruſt not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mercy of God. His arme is not yet abreuiated, &amp; ſhortned. He both can, and will helpe vs, ſo that wée call for his ayde, and ſuccour, and will not
<pb facs="tcp:7028:42"/> refuſe his grace, when it is offered vnto vs. Doth he not cry out by S. Paule,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.</note> &amp; plainly teſtifye, that he is rich vnto all them that call vpon him?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Peroratio.</head>
               <p>I Hartily deſire you, déerely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brethren in the Lorde, to take this my ſimple tretiſe in good part, whereby I, a weake member of yours, am deſirous to doe you good, being other members in the lorde, as farre foorth as I might, both for breuitie of time, &amp; alſo the health of my body not being perfite. I had léeuer comforte you face to face, if it might ſo be. But ſéeing it may not be ſo, I will ſomewhat make amendes, in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ready good will and charity towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des you, by prayer. Wherefore, I beſeeche Ieſus Chriſt, that true, and moſt approued meane, the moſt plentifull apothecary, that he will vouchſafe to make this phiſick for the ſoule, collected, and atchyued out of his apothecaries ſhoppe, that is to wit, out of the riche ſtorehouſe of holy ſcripture, to be effectual in your harts, that true fayth may encreaſe in you, the loue both towardes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7028:42"/> God, and your neyghbour may be feruent in you, that ye may be pacient in all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and aduerſitie, that ye diligently following Chriſt his example, may cleaue and ſticke faſt vnto him, euen to the yéelding vp of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt breath, in ſure hope of eternall life tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The ende of the Booke entituled, Phyſick for the ſoule.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:43"/>
            <head>A fourme and methode, <hi>or right order to</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the ſicke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou muſte for a ſurety determine with thy ſelfe, O Chriſtian, which art troubled and gréeued with ſickneſſe, that thou art not afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by hap, or chaunce, but by the purpoſe, and permiſſion of God. Whatſoeuer diſeaſe there be, calamitie, heauineſſe, or infelicity, which happeneth vnto the godlye, it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all by the determination, and will of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99.</note> which gouerneth all things. For in him we liue, moue, and haue our being. He made vs, and not we our ſelues. And doubt not, but he ſendeth this ſickneſſe, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, of his good, and fatherly loue, not to the entent that he would thereby deſtroy thée, but that he myght call thée to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that he myght ſtirre vp, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thy fayth.<note place="margin">Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</note> For afflictions are the ſure, and vndoubted ſignes, and tokens of Gods great mercy, and fauour towards vs. Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7028:43"/> ſayth:<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prouer.</hi> 13.</note>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.</note> Whom he loueth, him doth he correct, he ſcourgeth euery childe whom he receyueth. Thy moſt mercifull heauenlye father, which loueth thée earneſtly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his good purpoſe, and zeale towards thée, doth withholde, brydell, and mortifie thine olde man by this ſickneſſe, like as it were tyed with chaynes, that thou mayeſt the more gladly, and with the better good will, as it were faſten thy body vppon the croſſe, as a ſacrifyce offered vp with Chriſt. Therefore this thy diſeaſe, wherewith thou art troubled, is a fatherlye correction ſent vnto thée, not for that purpoſe, that thou ſhouldeſt be loſt, or caſt away, but that thou ſhouldeſt be made the better, and be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. God thy father peraduenture doth ſée, that thine olde Adam waxeth vntractable, immoderate, and vnruly, and ouermuch gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to affections, not able to gouerne, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to inhabite, or withhold himſelf. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he layeth this band or collar vpon him, he bindeth him faſt with theſe fetters, and chaynes, he ſhutteth him into this pryſon, and dungeon, he tyeth him with this clog, that he may bridel, that he may kepe down, and reſtreiue him, that he do not ſeduce, and
<pb facs="tcp:7028:44"/> caſt thy moſt déere, and precious ſoule into perill. The fleſh, and blood doe reſiſt, &amp; are more ſtrong in thée, than the ſpirite, &amp; here God is preſent with thy ſpirite, &amp; doth ayde him againſt the fierce, and vnbrideled will, and rebelling fleſhe, that he maye ſubdue, vanquiſhe, and bring it in ſubiection. If ſo be that thou ſhouldeſt haue good, and perfite helth of body, perchaunce the fleſhe, as it is prone, and ready vnto nothing but euil, had brought, and ſeduced thée into many, &amp; grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes againſt GOD, whereby his wrath ſtirred vp, &amp; prouoked againſt thée, ſhould make a waye for thy ſoule vnto hell, and malediction. Thy heauenly father pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting this dammage, and peril, carefull, and prouident for thée, and thy ſaluation, doth kéepe downe, and reſtraine, as it were with putting on a bridell vpon thy fleſhe, &amp; leadeth it away captiue, raging, &amp; rebelling againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite by all meanes poſſible, that it be not tumbled into the ſinck, &amp; puddle of ſinne, but that it be brought vnder, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come obedient vnto the ſpirite. Seing that this is the will of thy moſte louing father, and ſeing that all things ſhall redownde vnto thy profite and ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, take very good
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7028:44"/> héede that thou ſtriue not againſt the good will of God, and that thou be not contrarie to him, but ſuffer thou paciently, and pray, that his fatherly will bée done, that hée vſe thée at his pleaſure, and that thou wilt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but that ſhall ſéeme beſt vnto him, that al things may bée done vnto the lande, and glorie of God, &amp; that thou mayeſt haue his grace quietly and moderately to ſuffer his croſſe, layed vpon thée.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> For pacience bringeth experience, experience bringeth hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed. Here thou haſt matter, and occaſion to learne, and exerciſe pacience in all afflictions, and troubles. Firſt, thou doeſt learne, that God afflicteth, and puniſheth thée with a fatherly correction, and that thou learneſt by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. For except thou ſhouldeſt knowe by proofe, &amp; experience how wholeſome a thing it is for man wholy to commit himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to GOD, and to be obedient vnto his good will, and pleaſure. Euen as Dauid ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> it is good for mée that I haue béene in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thou were not able to conceiue certaine, and ſure hope of him, thou ſhouldeſt not know his fatherly loue, &amp; good will towards thee, which is hidden in ſecret, if thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:7028:45"/> not proue it before, by this croſſe and rodde. But when thou haſt learned it before by experience, and haſt now ſome taſt of that matter alreadie, thou doeſt not faint, and fall into deſperation by any afflictions, but thine hope moreouer encreaſeth, when thou haſt oftentymes tyred Gods preſent ayde, and helpe. And although he ſometime for a ſeaſon, as it were winking at the matter, doe ſuffer thée to ſticke faſt, and ſinke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to daungerous places, yet at the length not withſtanding he reacheth thée his helping hande, he taketh thée vp and doth preſerue thée. He ſuffereth thée ſometimes to ſwim and to be ouerwhelmed with waues of this lyfe, but he will not ſuffer thée to be vtterly drowned. Hereby thou mayſt aſcerteine thy ſelfe, that he will not forſake thée, or caſt thée awaye, ſeing that he hath ſo often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued thée, when thou waſt in daunger. Therefore by afflictions thou doeſt learne to conceiue, and nouriſhe ſure, and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hope of God, that thou mayeſt truſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in moſt gréeuous diſeaſes, &amp; puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, where there appéereth no ſuccour at all, being now inſtructed after what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he delyuereth, &amp; preſerueth his ſeruants.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7028:45"/> Thou haſt learned that God ſendeth afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon thée, not in his wrath, but in his fatherly loue. The which thing when thou art thorowlye perſwaded, and art taught by experience, thou mayeſt pacient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looke for Gods ayde and ſuccour, and not diſpaire, but conſtantlye truſt, that in the ende he will help thee, although he hide himſelfe, prolonging, and deferring thine ayde, and deliuerance neuer ſo long. And by this meanes thou ſhalt perceyue and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande at the laſt, that diſeaſe, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is not ſent vnto thée for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that thou therby ſhouldſt be deſtroyed, but that the glorie of God mought be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly ſhewed, and that all things mought turne vnto thy ſaluation. He that can after this maner commit, and giue himſelf wholy vnto God, beleuing, &amp; truſting in his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſhall neuer die. The which thing euen Chriſt himſelfe affirming w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an othe, leaſt happily we ſhould ſomwhat doubt, doth ſay: Verily, verily, if a man kéepe my worde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note> he ſhal neuer ſée death. And in an other place he ſaith: I am the way, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verity, and the life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 21.</note> He that beleueth on me, ſhall lyue, although he were dead. And whoſoeuer lyueth, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth
<pb facs="tcp:7028:46"/> on mée, ſhall neuer dye. Sée that thou diligently kéepe theſe words of Chriſt, faſtened in the bottome of thine hart, and herewith thou ſhalt lift vp, and ſtrengthen thy wauering minde. He that beleeueth on Chriſt, ſhal not taſte of death. He that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth on me (ſayth Chriſt) hath eternall life, and this is eternall lyfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 17.</note> that they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thée, to be true God, and him whome thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">Eternall lyfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth in this worlde.</note> Eternall lyfe firſt beginneth in this worlde.<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14.</note> For he, that hath Chriſt, hath the true life. For Chriſt is lyfe, and is the victoritie it ſelf. Therfore he will not deceyued vs,<note n="†" place="margin">2. <hi>Corin.</hi> 1.</note> but all the promiſes of God in him are yea, and are in him. Amen.</p>
            <p>And to the ende, that thou ſhouldeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubt, but that God wil performe his word, and make his promiſe good, he hath aſſured, and bounde himſelfe vnto thée, by a certeine peculiar league, and ſigne, put, and added vnto thy body. For he coueted, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired thy ſaluation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3.</note> when he ſent his ſonne into the world, to the intent he ſhould offer himſelfe, vnto death for thée. He did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make, and aſſure a league of grace through Chriſt, that he would fréely giue thée euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting lyfe, if thou beleue, and art baptiſed,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7028:46"/> that he woulde neuer forſake thee, that he will be thy father, that he will crowne thee with grace, and mercie.<note place="margin">Baptiſme is a ſeale of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> And thy baptſime is the ſeale, and token of this league, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto his promiſes being added, it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, that thou ſtick faſt vnto them. For he gaue this ſinge, that thou ſhouldeſt nothing doubt of his couenant, and promiſed grace. Thou art baptiſed into the death of Chriſt, as ſaint Paule ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> that his death ſhould be made thine, and that he ſhould make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction in all things for thée, and thou haſt put him on in thy baptiſme,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 3.</note> that thou ſhouldeſt wholy be in him, and hée in thée. Therefore baptiſme is a league, lifting vp, making merie, and quieting thy conſcience before god, as ſaint Peter beareth witneſſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.</note> that hee wyll neuer condemne thée for thy ſinnes. For thou iuſtified by fayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> art at peace with God. A quiet, calme, and paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied conſcience, is the true peace.<note place="margin">The true peace.</note> And thou haſt receiued baptiſme as a moſt ſure token, and certeine ſeale of this iuſtification, and remiſſion of ſinnes, that thou ſhouldſt ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly beléeue, that God will haue mercye on thée, that hée will preſerue and delyuer thée.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:47"/>
            <p>Now therefore, ſeing that God fauoreth thée, and will be thy father, and will neuer forſake thée, and ſeing that thou haſt recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued an infallible token, and teſtimony here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, commende, and vtterly giue all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and thy ſelfe alſo wholy vnto him, and be thou obedient vnto his good will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and thou muſt paciently abide, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his hande, whether he will haue thée to dye, or lyue, ſo that his owne bleſſed will may be done, vnto his owne praiſe, &amp; glory. Albeit it is not poſſible, that thou canſt be damned, if thou conſecrate, and dedicate thy ſelfe wholy vnto him, ſurely truſting in his mercie, promiſed for Chriſt his ſake. For he hath condicioned, that he will be thy father. And bicauſe he is true, when thou doeſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him to be thy father, and doeſt looke for, and hope to receyue all goodneſſe of him, he cannot but be thy father, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue thée, by what meanes ſoeuer he ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſeth thee for a little ſpace. Seing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he hath promiſed to be thy father, &amp; thou truſteſt vnto his promiſes: without all que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, he taketh earneſt care of thee, and all thine. Wherefore thou ſhalt commend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, not onely thine owne body, but alſo
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7028:47"/> thy wyfe and children, thy kinſfolkes and fréendes, and to be ſhort, all that thou haſt, and doubt not, but he will be vnto thée, in the ſteade of a verie father, a wyfe, a true fréend, and coſine. For hitherto he hath vſed thée, as a diſpenſatour, and ſteward in thoſe things. But now ſéeing that he will haue thée to lay aſide the function of this office: he wil appoint in thy roume an other ſteward for them, which ſhall diligently, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take care of them. If thou hope for this of him, and looke for it with a ful confidence of hart, there is no doubt, but he will do as I haue tolde thée. Wherefore put out of thy minde all care of them, and commit it vnto God. Be rather carefull for thy ſelfe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for thy ſoule, and thinke how to yéelde it vp vnto God.</p>
            <p>And ſeing that God hath fréely forgiuen thée all thy ſinnes for Chriſt his ſake, he will require nothing of thee at all for this his great, and ineſtimable benefite, but that thou againe forgiue, from the bottome of thine hart all them, which haue offended thée. And he doth promiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</note> that he wil remit all our treſpaſſes, if we forgiue other men there miſdéedes. Therefore when thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:7028:48"/> ſo forgiuen all offences vnfaynedly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou neuer reuiue them, nor call them vnto me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie againe, praye alſo for them, which haue done thée harme, according to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and example of Chriſt, and if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer, help them néeding thine aide, as much as thou mayeſt. If thou haue ſuch a minde voyde of ſtrife, enuie, malice, and wrath, thou haſt alſo a ſigne and token, that God hath forgiuen thée thy ſinnes. For fayth whereby thine hart is purified, and clenſed, exerciſing hir ſelfe, and bringing forth hir fruits, according to Gods infinite benifits, cannot chooſe but likewiſe forgiue, and doe good vnto hir neighbour. This fruit of loue, and charitie teſtifieth, and doth aſcerteine thée,<note place="margin">A liuely fayth, bringeth foorth true fruites.</note> that thy faith is a true, &amp; a liuely faith, ſeing that ſhe bringeth forth good, and true fruites.<note n="†" place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.</note> This is the thing, that ſaint Peter would haue, whereas he biddeth vs to giue the more diligence, to make our calling, and election ſure by good workes. For he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that thoſe workes are witneſſes, and ſignes, that thou art choſen, and adopted of God, to be his ſonne, vnto the ioyes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſaluation.</p>
            <p>But thou ſhalt not hope, déerely beloued,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7028:48"/> that God will forgiue thée thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">Payne cannot merite, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes.</note> for the payne and gréeuouſneſſe of thy croſſe &amp; ſickneſſe.<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1.</note> For there is none other ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ther is none other recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for thy ſinnes, then the onely death of Chriſt. God truely reſpecteth none other thing in this caſe, hée accepteth none other thing, but his déerely beloued ſonne. This is the lambe of God, which taketh away the ſinnes of the world. And this thy ſickneſſe and paynes cannot make ſatiſfaction vnto God ſo muche as for thy leaſt offence, muche leſſe, can it deſerue ſaluation. As S. Paule teſtifyeth ſaying: I ſuppoſe that the afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this lyfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> are not worthy of the glory, which ſhall be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon vs. No creature,<note place="margin">Peter ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Act. 4 there is no ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than in Chriſt.</note> neyther in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, neyther in earth, no Angell coulde mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate, and pacifie the wrath of GOD the father, then this thy diſeaſe and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affliction, is much leſſe able to aſwage it. And farder it was requiſite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he, which ſhould pacifie that wrath, and reconcile god vnto man, ſhould be both God and man, as one ready to pleade, and make interceſſion betwéene God being offended, &amp; man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Therefore it behoued the ſonne of God to be made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he might appeaſe
<pb facs="tcp:7028:49"/> and ſatiſfie the wrath of his father, &amp; deliuer vs from it, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet witneſſeth ſaying: Hée taketh away our infirmities,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53.</note> &amp; beareth our paynes. God hath layd our iniquities v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, I haue ſmitten him (ſayth god) for the ſinnes of my people.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2.</note> And ſ. Peter fayth: By whoſe ſtripes we ar healed. Thy ſinnes therefore are forgiuen thée for this thy lord Chriſt his ſake, and for none other thing in all the world. For none afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, be they neuer ſo bitter, and gréeuous, can helpe vs. Chriſt is our only iuſtification,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſatiſfaction and ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note>God hath made him to be ſinne for vs, that knew no ſinne, that we by his meanes ſhould be righteous. Wherfore, if thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Gala.</hi> 3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.</note> thou art nowe becomme the ſonne of God. If thou be the ſonne of God, thou art alſo the heire of God, and the fellow heyre with Chriſt. If ſo be that eternall lyfe be the inheritaunce, and gift of God, as ſaint Paule doth call it, thou canſt not deſerue it by the paynes, and gréefe of thy ſickneſſe. But God woulde haue thée puniſhed wyth this diſeaſe vnto this ende, &amp; purpoſe, that thou ſhouldſt therby keepe downe, breake, and mortifie this thine olde man, that at the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7028:49"/> length he maye ceaſe from committing of ſinne,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> the ende whereof commeth onely by this corporall death. And for this cauſe wée muſte dye, that our ſoules may depart vnto euerlaſting ſaluation. For death is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gate,<note place="margin">Death is the ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe.</note> and entraunce vnto eternall lyfe, where, in the ende we are deliuered from all cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.</note> myſeries, and wretchedneſſe, from all errours, and deceytes of the diuell, that we ſhall no more be defiled with the moſte filthy ſpottes of ſinne, neyther ſhall we be ſeduced into hereſies, or errours, neither be caſt headlong into deſperation.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> Then there ſhall be an ende of all euills, of all aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and diſcommodities. Then ſhall we reſt in the lorde, and ſhall obtaine lyfe, and euerlaſting ioyes. Death therfore is not to be deteſted, and abhorred, yea, rather it is earneſtly to be deſired, and imbraced, ſeing that we paſſe thorow it into eternall ioyes. And that is a moſt true ſaying, which ſaint Paule ſpeaketh:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> That all things vnto the godly, ſhall turne vnto good. Truely death vnto the worlde ſéemeth to be a thing moſt odious, moſt horrible, and cruell, but vnto the beleeuers it is moſte ſwéete, pleaſant, and acceptable. Although our olde Adam
<pb facs="tcp:7028:50"/> doth tremble at hir comming, abhorreth, &amp; eſcheweth hir. Our inward man notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is readie, chéerefull, quick, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to die, ſeing that he vnderſtandeth and knoweth, that he ſhall be deliuered from al filthineſſe of ſinne, wickedneſſe, vice, and wredchedneſſe by hir, and ſhall go forth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall ioyes.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>How thoſe are to be comforted, which lye in the daunger of death.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD thy good and moſte lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing father, hauing compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on thée, déerely beloued, doth call thée out of this moſt miſerable and wretched lyfe, wylling to tranſlate &amp; bring thée vnto himſelfe, into the perpetuall ioyes of the celeſtiall life. Therfore giue and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende thy ſelfe and all thine, wholy vnto him, and whatſoeuer he will haue done, will thou the ſame alſo.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 26. <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>Io.</hi> 6. <hi>Lu.</hi> 23</note> And ſay, thy wil be done O God my father, and not mine. Cry vnto Chriſt as the théefe did, which hanged on the croſſe: Remember mée O lord when
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7028:50"/> thou commeſt into thy kingdome. Crie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the publican:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 18.</note> O lord be mercifull vnto me a wretched ſinner. Crie inſtantly with the woman of Cana, that heathen gentile: Oh ſonne of Dauid, haue mercie on mée.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> And doubt not, but Chriſt will heare thée calling vnto him, and haue compaſſion on thée. He will forgiue thee thy ſinnes, and thou ſhalt be with him in paradiſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, take thou holde by this Chriſt, ſticke faſt vnto him, and ſée that thou commit thy ſoule vnto him. Crie thou with this Chriſt crucified vnto GOD, which is father vnto you both: In thée, O lorde, I put my truſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.</note> let mée neuer bée put to confuſion, delyuer me in thy righteouſneſſe. Bowe downe thine eare to mée, make haſt to delyuer me. Be thou my ſtrong rock, and houſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that thou mayeſt ſaue mée. Thou art my ſtrong rock, and my caſtle, be thou my guide alſo. Into thy handes I commend my ſpirite. Crie thou with Dauid alſo: O lorde thou art my ſtrength, the lorde is my ſtony rock, and my defence, God is my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and my buckler, the horne alſo of my ſaluation. Vnto thée, O lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.</note> haue I lifted vp my ſoule, my God I haue put my truſt
<pb facs="tcp:7028:51"/> in thée. O let me not be confounded. Leade me forth in thy truth. For thou art the God of my ſaluation. Call to remembraunce, O lorde, thy tender mercies, and thy louing kindneſſe, which hath bene euer of olde. Oh remember not the offences of my youth, but according to thy mercie, thinke thou vpon me O lord, for thy goodneſſe. For thy names ſake O lorde bée mercifull vnto my ſinne, for it is great. Turne thée vnto mée &amp; haue mercy vpon me, O bring thou me out of my troubles. Forgiue mée all my ſinnes, O keepe my ſoule and deliuer mée. Let me not bée confounded. For I haue put my truſt in thée. If thou call for Gods ayde, and ſuccour after this maner, God will helpe thée in a conuenient time, and will ſay, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the pſalme:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.</note> Bicauſe he hath ſet his loue vpon me, I will therfore delyuer him, I will ſet him vp, bicauſe he hath knowne my name. He ſhall call vpon me, and I will heare him, yea, I am with him in trouble, I will deliuer him, and bring him to honor. Wherefore, O thou chriſtian, here fight a good fight, fight thou valiantly, ſtoutely, &amp; conſtantly, as it becommeth a true chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an to doe.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:7028:51"/>
               <p>Beware thou giue no ground, nor go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, there is no perill. Thou fighteſt not here alone. But the king Ieſus Chriſt is thy captaine in this agony. Follow him go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before thée in this conflict. This thy ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitaine ſhalbe thy reuenger, &amp; he ſhall ſaue, and defende thée in this battell from all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enimiys of thy ſoule, from all perill, &amp; from al calamitie. He is not a king as others are, but he is of infinit, and vnſpeakable power. He hath vanquiſhed, and ſubdued for thy ſake, death, ſathan, and hell.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 25. <hi>Oſcae.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> Death is ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp into the victorie. Chriſt died for thée. Therefore eternall death, hath no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer on thée. Chriſt deſcended into hell, that he might deliuer thée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this eternall dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Be thou therfore of a valiant, &amp; ſtout courage, runne into the front of the battell with a bold hart, put away all feare, here is no daunger. There is no cauſe why thou ſhouldeſt feare the ſeuere, &amp; ſtreight iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> Ieſus Chriſt is thy mediatour before God. He is thine aduocate, &amp; patrone. He is both thy biſhop, &amp; prieſt. He hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled thée vnto God, and hath reſtored vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you his fatherly loue, which was aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from thée, for thy ſinnes ſake. God now
<pb facs="tcp:7028:52"/> is now thy father for Chriſt his ſake.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay.</hi> 63. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.</note> He ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth care of thée. He entéerly loueth thée, as his moſt tender childe. Now ſéeing that this ſo mighty a king ſtandeth on thy ſide: who ſhall be able to trouble thée? Who ſhall be able to aſſault &amp; inuade thée? Who, I pray thée, ſhall be able to doe thée wrong? What daunger can there be? Harcken what ſaint Paule ſayth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> If God (ſayeth he) be on our ſide, who can be againſt vs? Which hath not ſpared his owne ſonne, but hath yéelded him vp for vs all, howe can it be, that he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo will not giue vs all things w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him? Who ſhall go about to laye anye crime againſt Gods elect? It is God that iuſtifieth. Who is he then that can condemne? It is Chriſt that died, yea rather, which is rayſed vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and is at the right hand of God, and there maketh interceſſion for vs. Who ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of God? I am thorowlye perſwaded, that neyther death, neither life, neither heigth, neither depth, neither any other creature, can be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vs from the loue of God, which is in our lord Ieſus Chriſt. Séeing that therfore, Chriſt is giuen thee, with al his riches, with all his righteouſneſſe, innocency, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7028:52"/> Eternall life is giuen thée alſo. Sainct Paule teſtifying the ſame, vnto the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, ſayth:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 1</note> That Chriſt is made of God to vs, wiſdome, and alſo righteouſneſſe, and ſanctifying, and redemption. Therefore, ſée that thou haue all thy hope, and confidence placed and fixed vpon this Chriſt, and vpon this corner ſtone. This ſtone is a ſure, ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,<note place="margin">This ſtone is Chriſt. 1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 28.</note> and firme foundation, wherevnto thou mayſt leane, and ſafely commit thy ſelfe. No tempeſt, be it neuer ſo black, and boyſterous, no ſhower, no ſtormes, are able to throwe downe, and ouerturne this foundation. Let all thy hope and aide (I ſay) be placed, and ſet on this Chriſt, caſt thy ſelfe vpon him, ſticke faſt vnto him, let no temptation, or calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be able to withdrawe, and pull thée from him, although all things ſeeme to happen vnto thée very abſurdly, and ouerthwartly. Although fleſhe, and blood, doe interprete it farre otherwiſe, and reaſon thinke it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, although the deuill doth nowe and then whiſper in thy minde, ſaying: That thou art vndone, that God is highly offended with thee, that thou haſt deſerued the paine of hell fire, and that thou muſte be damned. For faith is a ſubſtaunce, that is to wit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.</note> an
<pb facs="tcp:7028:53"/> expectation of things hoped for,<note place="margin">Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis.</note> that is of promiſes, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is as much to ſay, as a ſure argument, and knowledge of things that are not ſéene.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.17.</note> Thou muſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue with that holy Patriarch Abraham in hope, ouer and aboue hope. Thy faith, and hope muſte reſiſt, and ſet it ſelfe againſt all thoſe things, which eyther blinde reaſon ſuggeſteth, either that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> our moſt ſubtile, and by all meanes moſt crafty enimy, going about to worke vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyt, and our deſtruction, doth inſtill and poure into vs. Wherfore thou muſt learne well the maner and cuſtome of God, which he vſeth in preſeruing thoſe that are his. Looke whome he will lift vp into heauen, him will he firſt ſeeme to bring downe vnto hell.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.</note> Looke whom he entendeth to quicken, him will he firſt mortifie and kill. Vppon whom he mindeth to ſhew his notable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and fauor, he firſt maketh ſemblance, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, as though he would co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne him. Wherfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou perceyueſt none other thing, but preſent death, when God ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be gréeuouſlye offended with thée, when that thou thynkeſt that he is gone moſt fardeſt from thée, and that he hath vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7028:53"/> forſaken thée, as one refuſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned: then is he moſt néereſt vnto thée, ready to defend, and deliuer thée, he then lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thee moſt eſpecially, then thou art chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly regarded of him. For when trouble, and affliction commeth vpon vs, then doth he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his mercye, according to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſaying:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.</note> For his wrath endureth but the twinkling of an eye, he will not be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry for euer. For like as a father pitieth his owne children:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.</note> euen ſo is the lord merciful vnto them, that feare him. For he knoweth wherof we be made, he remembreth that we are but duſt. But the mercifull goodneſſe of the lorde, endureth for euer, and euer. The lord is full of compaſſion, and mercye, long ſuffering, and of great goodneſſe. Wherfore ſubmit, put vnder, giue, and commend thy ſelfe wholy vnto Chriſt, cloſing thine eyes, &amp; reiecting the iudgement of thy ſenſes, &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, take it in good parte, howſoeuer he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth thée. Thou muſt not eſtéeme, and conſider death, and horrour, or the dolours of death, according to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of thine eyes, ſenſe, and reaſon: but according to the worde of God. Dauid ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.</note> Right déere in the ſight of the lorde is the death of his
<pb facs="tcp:7028:54"/> ſaints. Lykewiſe he ſayeth: Bleſſed are the dead,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14 <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note> which die in the lorde. Chriſt alſo ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: He that beléeueth on mée, ſhall not taſt of death. If any thing therefore come into thy memorie, which attempteth to turne thée away from Chriſt, and to caſt thée into deſperation, put all that out of thy minde, and ſtick thou faſt vnto the liuely worde of God, meditate, and ponder thereon, print it in thy minde, repeating it now and then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong. For thou canſt neuer vnderſtand by the conſideration, and ſharpneſſe of reaſon, how it may be done, that by death thou ſhalt paſſe vnto the true lyfe, how thou yéelding vp thy ghoſt mayeſt depart here hence, how thy ſoule maye be preſerued, and reſt in the lorde, euen vntill the laſt day, and how alſo thy body being rotten, conſumed, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured with wormes, maye come forth at the laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with a new, and a beaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull ſhape. Reaſon cannot comprehende this, faith onely can. Therefore, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times thinke thou vpon the articles of thy beléefe, diligently conſider, and attentiuely examine euery particular thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:7028:54"/>
               <head>After what ſort he is to bee called vpon, which lyeth at the point of death.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow ſée, déerely beloued in Chriſt, that thou fight a good fight. Sée that thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and valiantly defende thy ſelf, throughly faſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thine hart, the promiſes of Chriſt thy redeemer. I am the reſurrection,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11.</note> and the lyfe, ſayeth Chriſt. He that beléeueth on me, ſhall lyue, and ſhall neuer ſée death. Chriſt taking vpon him the nature of man, ſubiect to the infirmities of our eſtate, did offer vp himſelfe to be a ſacrifice for our ſinnes, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon the aultar of the croſſe. He by his bleſſed blood, did purge, and clenſe the ſinnes of all mankynde. This Chriſte will not forſake thée, he taketh a regarde of thée. Thou canſt ſuffer no iniurie, or calamitie, ſeing that Chriſt doth preſerue, and defende thée.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 2. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10.</note> The ſure foundation of God ſtandeth faſt hauing this ſeale, the lorde knoweth which are his, my ſhéepe héere my voice, and I know them, and they folow mée, and I
<pb facs="tcp:7028:55"/> giue vnto them eternall lyfe, and they ſhall neuer periſhe, neyther ſhall any man pluck them out of my hand. My father, which gaue them me is greater then all, and no man is able to take them out of my fathers hand. And I and my father are one. Wherefore, O déerely beloued in Chriſt, commend thy ſoule vnto God thy father, which loueth thée ſingularlye. Crie out with thy brother Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 27. <hi>Luc.</hi> 27.</note> hanging on the croſſe: Into thy handes, O father, I giue and commend my ſpirite. God the father of all mercie, bring thée vnto euerlaſting lyfe, and preſerue thée vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ioyfull reſurrection of his laſt iudgement. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The ende of the fourme and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, or right order, to comfort the ſick.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:7028:55"/>
            <head>¶ A prayer to be ſayde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God for the ſick.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie, euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, which art woont amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt thy ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry diſciplines, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfolde chaſtiſements, wherewith thou doeſt prouoke, and allure vs vnto thée, to bridle our fleſhe with diuers diſeaſes, the ſecuritie thereof taken awaye by perillous ſickneſſe, and doeſt both admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe vs of the ende of oure naughtie lyfe paſt, and alſo of ymminent death through paines, which are hir fore meſſengers, and likewiſe of thy iudgement in the laſt daye, and of the eternall lyfe to come, which ſhall be reſerued for the good, and godly vnto glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and felicitie, but for the euil vnto ſhame and condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hell fyre. Of the which things, fleſhe being let runne at hir owne will, hath no remembrance. But now we perceyue, this ſeelye man is layed on his bedde, by his impayred health, vnto whome
<pb facs="tcp:7028:56"/> is ſtirred vp the féeling of his ſinnes, and the ymage of death often flyeth, as it were before his eyes. We wretches therefore, which looke for the lyke houre of aduerſitie, acording to the condition of our nature, doe beſeeche, &amp; deſire thée togither with him, that thou practiſe not righteous iudgement with him for his deſerts, for our lord Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, which hath made ſatiſfaction on the croſſe, for the offences of this ſicke body, and vs all. But rather graunt hym, as to one redéemed, grace, and ſtrength of mind, that he maye quietly take this thy fatherly diſcipline, and viſitation, paciently beare it, and that he may ſuffer wyllingly with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite obedience himſelfe, to be ſubiect, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſant vnto the good will, and pleaſure of thée, his puniſher. Succour him in all his aduerſities, and be thou vnto him a refuge, and a defence againſt this inſtant daunger, wherewith he is now in perill, eſpecially of his reueled conſcience, the ſecret ſinnes of his hart doe accuſe him vnto thée. Therefore ſet thou againſt it for his preſeruation, the moſte bitter torments, and voluntarie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of thy ſonne Chriſt, which did beare our infirmities,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> and accompliſhed the paine
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7028:56"/> due vnto vs, beeing made ſinne for vs,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.</note> whilſt that he died for our ſinnes, which he waſhed away, with his precious blood, and riſing from the deade for our iuſtification, was made our perfite redéemer. Let him perceiue through faith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force of theſe fruits and benifites. Let him being oppreſſed in this miſery, féele thine aide, and let him taſt, in this moment of time, ſome fruite of ſuche benifits, and gifts in Chriſt. Bring to paſſe euen nowe by true fayth, that there maye be offered vnto him ſo great a treaſure of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie, that is, I meane the forgiueneſſe of his ſinnes for Chriſt his ſake, which by the miſterie of the preaching of his worde, as is before ſaide, and the vſe of his ſacramentes frequented in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, is offered vnto him, that he maye effectually, and of a ſuertie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it to his comfort, ayde, and defence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the troubles of his conſcience, grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly accuſing him, and the ſubtiltie of the deuill. And alſo that the ſame faith maye be vnto him, an armour, wherewith he being defenced may enter through death into lyfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>n he taking hold, may enioy the ſame for euer. Therefore, O heauenly father, we doe wholy commit him vnto thée, for thou
<pb facs="tcp:7028:57"/> ſhalt heale him, bicauſe he is ſicke. Hée is weake, thou ſhalt ſtrengthen him, he lyeth a long, thou ſhalt ſet him vp, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth his ſpottes, and vncleaneſſe, thou ſhall waſhe him, he is wounded, thou ſhalt cure him, he is feareful, thou ſhalt giue him courage. And for bicauſe thou knoweſt all things, and canſt beſtowe according to thy wil, thou ſhalt ſatiſfie him. For he is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gréeued with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, and thirſt after thée. Imbrace him. For he ſtraight waye flyeth vnto thée, and make hym conſtant to fulfill thy commaundements. And to be briefe, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue him all things, wherwith he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked thy heauie diſpleaſure againſt him. Graunt him in the ſteade of death, life, with thée in glorye. But if we ſhall néede him, in thy vineyarde, in this mortall life, and that he maye be imbettred vnto the example of Chriſt, then preſerue him, vntill that he be increaſed with more ample benifites. Thy will notwithſtanding, which alwayes is beſt, be euer fulfilled. Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t all thoſe things vnto vs, and this ſicke body, through Ieſus Chriſt only, thy ſonne our lord, which is our only redeemer, &amp; helper, and which brought the théefe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe with him into Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7028:57"/> for the example, and great comfort of al ſinners, which liueth, and reigneth with thée, in the vnitie of the holy ghoſt, one God world without end. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>¶ A prayer to be ſayd vnto Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde Ieſu, which art the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye health of all men liuing, &amp; the euerlaſting life of them, which die in faith, I giue, and ſubmit my ſelfe wholy vnto thy moſte bleſſed will, whether it pleaſeth thée, that this my ſéelie ſoule ſhall tary any longer in the manſion of this my wretched bodye to ſerue thée, or whether thou wilt haue it to depart out of this world, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that the thing cannot periſh, which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mited vnto thy mercy. Willingly now I leaue this fraile, and ſinfull fleſh, in hope of the reſurrection, which ſhall reſtore it vnto me againe far better than now it is. I beſech thée, that thou wilt ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen my ſoule, with thy grace, againſt all temptations, and that thou wilt compaſſe me about, and defende me with the ſhielde of thy mercy, againſt al the aſſaultes of ſathan, wherewith in time
<pb facs="tcp:7028:58"/> paſt, thou madeſt thy martyrs inuincible a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt horrible torments, and moſte cruell deathes. I ſée, and confeſſe, that in my ſelfe there is no help of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but all my hope, and confidence is in thine vnſpeakable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I haue no merites, or good workes, which I maye alleage before thée, of ſinnes, alas, I ſée a great heape, but through thy mercy, and righteouſneſſe, I ſhall be recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the number of the iuſte: Thou waſt borne for my ſake: Thou didſt ſuffer both hunger, and thirſt for my ſake: Thou didſt preach, and teache, faſt, and praye, for my ſake: Thou didſt all good works in this life for my ſake: Thou gaueſt thy moſt precious bodie vnto death vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe for my ſake. Let all theſe things profite me, which thou haſt fréely giuen mée, which haſt giuen thy ſelfe for me. Let thy blood waſhe awaye the ſpots of mine offences. Let thy righteouſnes couer, and hide mine vnrighteouſneſſe. Let thy merites make me acceptable before the moſt high Iudge. Increaſe thy grace in me, as peril encreaſeth, leaſt faith ſhould wauer in mée, leaſt my hope ſhoulde ſtacker, leaſt my charitie ſhould ware cold, leaſt humaine weakeneſſe ſhould be ouercome, by the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7028:58"/> of death. But after that death poſſeſſeth my bodilye eyes, yet let not the eyes of my mind be turned away from thée. And when death hath take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away the vſe of my tongue, yet let my hart inſtantly cry, and ſay vnto thée:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Into thy hands I commend my ſpirite (O lorde) to whom be all honor, and glorye, worlde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out end. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:59"/>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:7028:59"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A Sermon of pacience, <hi>of the conſummation of this world,</hi> of the ſecond comming of the lorde, the <hi>euerlasting ioyes of the righteous, the paines of the</hi>
               </hi> wicked, and of other things, written by ſaint Iohn <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> patriarch at Conſtantinople. Iohn <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylus,</hi> being the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitour thereof, out of Gréeke into Latine, and tranſlated out of Latin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into Engliſhe, by H. Thorne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He lyfe of godly men, is verie nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and bright. And by what meanes ſhould it ſhine, but through pacience? Therefore imbrace pacience,<note place="margin">Pacience is the mother of Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.</note> as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Fortitude. For the Pſalmiſt giueth vs admoniſhment ſaying: Tarry thou the lords leaſure, and kéepe his wayes. And ſaint Paule, to the ende thou ſhouldſt
<pb facs="tcp:7028:60"/> poſſeſſe this vertue ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> Affliction wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pacience, which if thou exerciſe, thou ſhalt finde hope, the fountaine of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For hope maketh not aſhamed. Be thou therefore ſubiect and obedient vnto the lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37. 1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2. <hi>Iaco.</hi> 4.</note> and pray vnto him, &amp; thou ſhalt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by find that thing, which is not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned: that is to wit, he will giue thée all thine harts deſire. Who is more happy than he, which hath in poſſeſſion the beneuolent eares of ſo mighty a king? Who wiſheth not to haue the iudges eares ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, &amp; at his commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> Thou (déerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued) art the workman &amp; laborer of vertue. Chriſt hath hyred thée into his vineyarde.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 20. <hi>Gala.</hi> 6.</note> Whiles thou haſt yet time, do good works. Harken what ſainct Paule ſayeth: Looke what a man ſoweth, euen the ſame ſhall he reape. Sow in the ſpirit, and thou ſhalt reap eternal life.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gala.</hi> 6.</note> For he that ſoweth in his body, reapeth corruption of his bodye. And heare what another counſell giuer ſayth: Sowe righteouſneſſe for your ſelues, and you ſhal gather the fruite of righteouſnes. Let it not lothe thée to take paines. There is an hope of harueſt, and fruite time. For where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictes are, there are rewardes. Where there
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7028:60"/> are contentions, there are honours.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 4</note> Where battell is, there is a crowne alſo. Haue thou a regard herevnto, and arme thy ſelfe vnto pacience. Let him alwayes ſounde in thine eares, which crieth with the ſainctes: Be of good courage, that thine hart maye be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, abide the lords leiſure,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.</note> vſe and exerciſe thy field. This life is thy field, take vnto thée a good toole, I meane the old and the new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument. Hedge thy ferme, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the brembles of doctrine, prayer, and faſting. If thou haue ſuch a hedge, the beaſt (I ſaye the diuell) can not enter in. Toile thy ſoule as a good vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. And euen as the keepers of vineyards, doe clap with their handes, crie with their voice, and with ſuch like noiſes, do kéepe off the wayt layers: So cry thou out alſo with praiers, ſing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the melodye of pſalmes, and thou ſhalt put to flight that foxe and wicked beaſt, as who ſayth the diuell. Of the which foxe the ſcripture maketh mention, ſaying: Take ye the foxes. &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.</note> Alwayes watch thyne enimy, if he ſhoot at thine hart, with vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full concupiſcence. If he ſling into thy ſoule, filthye cogitations,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>Teſſa.</hi> 5.</note> put foorth the ſhielde of faith, turne about the helmet of hope, take vp the ſword of the ſpirit, that is the worde
<pb facs="tcp:7028:61"/> of God. And thou being thus armed, ſhalt be able to defende thine enimy, and ſée that thou he not faint harted in the conflict,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Petr.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> but in al things be ſober, and wel aduiſed, &amp; ſay thus with thy ſelfe. We be not ignorant of his ſubtilties.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</note> Reioyce always, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: Let your ſoftneſſe be knowen vnto all men. Let the feare of God ſhine in thine hart, that thou become not a fugitiue ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, that thou be not a fearful, and ſluggiſh labourer, leaſt thou happily léeſe thy crown. This life is ſhort. But the ſentence of gods iudgement, is permanent, &amp; endleſſe. Thou conſidering this, mayeſt boldlye tell thine hart, and ſaye with the holye prophet: Be ſtrong,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.</note> and tary thou the lords leyſure, and he ſhall comfort thine hart. Follow Dauid his example,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17.</note> and ſlea thine enimy by the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of one ſtone. The angels ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by thée, beholding thy life.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> For ſ. Paule ſayth: We are become a gaſing ſtocke vnto the worlde, both vnto angels, &amp; vnto men. If they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that thou haſt the vpper hand, they wil reioyce in thy well doing. But if y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> bée ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, they will ſorowfully depart, not being able to looke on thée, &amp; in the contrary part, the deuils wil ſcorne thée. Therfore take vp
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7028:61"/> the feare of God in the ſtead of a ſword. For the feare of God is like a two edged ſworde, cutting off all euill concupiſcence, &amp; deſiers. And alſo haue thou alwayes in minde the laſt day,<note place="margin">The laſt day.</note> when the heauens ſet on fire ſhalbe diſſolued. For the burning elements ſhall melt. The earth, &amp; all that is thereon made,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 24. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2. <hi>EZech.</hi> 32. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 13. <hi>Ioel.</hi> 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. 1. <hi>Teſ.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 3.</note> ſhal be brent, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtarres ſhal fal down, as leaues, and the ſunne, and moone ſhall be darkned, and ſhall not giue their light, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſonne of God ſhall be ſéene, and ſhall come downe from heauen vnto the earth, and the powers of heauen ſhall be moued, when the aungels ſhall runne hither, and thither, the ſound of trumpets ſhall be hard, fire ſhall burne before him, and he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring about ſhall purge all the world with fire, and in his circuite there ſhalbe a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tempeſt. There ſhal be ſuch earthquakes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> and lightnings, as neuer ſhall be the lyke, nor haue bene euen vnto this daye, in ſo much that the very powers of heauen, ſhall be taken with great trembling.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 3.</note> What ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men, deerely beloued in Chriſt, then ought we to be, at that time? What feare, and what horror, will there then come on vs? Thinke with thy ſelfe, how the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites
<pb facs="tcp:7028:62"/> in the wilderneſſe, were not able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the dimneſſe and darkneſſe of the ayer, and the voyce of God ſpeaking out of the middle of the fire,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> but willed that he ſhould no more ſpeak vnto them, for they were not able to abyde him, when he did hyde the greateſt part of his maieſtie, althoughe he came downe not offended with them, nor ſpake he vnto them wrathfully.</p>
            <p>Therefore conſider this, if they were not able to abide his comming, which comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, when that neyther the burning heauens were diſſolued, neyther the earth, and that is in it, was burnte, when that neyther they which ſounde the Trumpet did blow, as that trumpet ſhalbe ſounded, which ſhall rayſe vp al them, that haue ſlept from the beginning of the world, neyther any other of the terrible things to come, did then happen: how ſhall we do when he ſhal come downe with intollerable wrath,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the lord. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and ſhall ſit vppon the throne of hys glory, and ſhall call the earth. Euen from the Eaſt, vnto the Weaſt, and from all the coſtes of the earth, that he may diſcerne, and knowe his people, and giue to euery man, according vnto his deſerts, what men (alas)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7028:62"/> behooueth vs to be, when that we ſhal ſtand ſtripped and naked, readie to bée brought foorth vnto the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeat? Where then ſhall that painted colour, and the force and ſtrength of the fleſhe become? then where ſhall that deceitfull and vnprofitable beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the pleaſantneſſe of mans voyce, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent &amp; ſhameleſſe babling become? Where then is the trimming, and decking vp with clothes, and the delight &amp; pleaſure, of moſt foule and filthie ſinne? Where then are they which drinke wyne with pyping and ſinging, and haue no regarde or reſpect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the workes of GOD? where then is the contempt, &amp; deſpiſing of them, which nowe lyue without feare. Then where is delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and nyſitie. For all thoſe things ſhall paſſe away, and ſhall be diſſolued as the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ayre?<note place="margin">Loke for this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. <hi>Sapi.</hi> 5.</note> Where then is the gréedie deſire of money and riches, and vnmercifulneſſe, hir continuall companion? Where then is pride, which diſdaineth all men, &amp; thinketh hir ſelfe to be ſomewhat? Where then is the vaine and vnprofitable glorie of man, the great might &amp; tirannie? Where then is the king, the prince, the capitaine? Where then are the puffed vp magiſtrates, contemning
<pb facs="tcp:7028:63"/> God, in compariſon of their owne riches? When they ſhall perceyue, that this ſaying muſt bée ſpoken of them: They maruailed, they are moued, they are troubled, feare is come vpon them:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oſcae.</hi> 13. <hi>Iere.</hi> 50. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> there ſhall be ſorowes, as of a woman trauailing with child, they ſhal be conſumed with a veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſpirit. Where then ſhal be come the wiſedome of the wiſe, with all there newe inuentions? Wo bee vnto them. They are moued, they are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, as a dronken man, and all there wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſwalowed vp.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 3.</note> Where then is the worldly wiſe, the ſcribe, and the treaſurer, of this vaine world. Way, and conſider, déere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued, what maner of men, we ought to be, when y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt yeelde an accompt of all, that we haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne, as well ſmall, as great things. For vntill that we according to iuſt iudgement, fully make ſatiſfaction: what ſhall our eſtate, and condicion bée in that houre, and how carefull ſhall we bée, that we maye obtaine fauour, in the ſight of God?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> And what ioy ſhall we haue, which ſhall be placed on the right hande of God? How then ſhall we féele our ſelues, when that all the ſaintes of God ſhall gréete vs? Abraham ſhall ſalute thée, Iſaac, and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7028:63"/> Moyſes, Noe, Iob, Dauid, and all the holy prophetes, apoſtles, and martirs, and all good men, which haue pleaſed God, in the lyfe of there fleſhe. And how many ſhalt thou there heare, whoſe lyfe thou ſhalt haue in admiration, whome thou wouldeſt euen now wyllingly ſée? They will there come vnto thée, reioyſing at thy ſaluation. After what ſort ſhal we then be affected? How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable ſhall that ioy bée, when the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome king ſhall ſay vnto them, which ſtand on his right hande:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> Come ye bleſſed of my father, &amp; take to your inheritance, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which was prepared for you, from the beginning of the worlde? Then ſhalt thou receyue a moſt decent kingdome,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sapi.</hi> 5.</note> and crown of beautie at the lordes hand, and after that ſhalt raigne with Chriſt. Then ſhalt thou inherite al theſe eternall things,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Timo.</hi> 4.</note> which God hath ordained for them, that loue him. Then ſhalt thou euer afterward be without dread, and heauineſſe. Ponder, and conſider, what it is to raigne with Chriſt in heauen. For as I haue tolde thée, thou ſhalt receyue a diademe, at the hande of the lorde, and ſhalt euer after raigne with Chriſt. Thinke with thy ſelfe, what a thing it is, to beholde the
<pb facs="tcp:7028:64"/> face of God, for euer, what a brightneſſe hath it? For then there ſhall be no ſunne to giue the day light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 60.</note> as Eſay ſayeth, and the riſing of the Moone, ſhall not lighten the night:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 64. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> But the lord God ſhall be thine eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall light, and thy glorie. Beholde what ioyes are layed vp in ſtore for them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare the lord, and kéepe his commaundements?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note>Conſider againe alſo, the perdition of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, when they ſhall be brought foorth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the terrible iudgement ſeat of God, with how great confuſion then ſhall they be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before the iuſt iudge? hauing not one worde to aunſwere, how ſhall they be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> when the lorde ſhall ſpeake vnto them in his wrath, and vexe them in his ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> ſaying, depart from me ye wicked into eternall fyre, which is prepared for the deuill, and his Angels. Alas what miſerie, and affliction ſhall there ſpirit ſuffer, when that all men ſhall crie out aloude, ſaying: Let the ſinners be turned into hell,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.</note> and all nations which forget God. What time wil they howle out, wayling and lamenting, when they ſhall bée caried awaye, that they maye be cruelly tormented, world without ende? what place (alas) is that, where is
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7028:64"/> wayling and gnaſhing of téeth, called hell, the which ſathan himſelfe abhorreth, what is that <hi>(Gehenna)</hi> fyre vnquenchable,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 66. <hi>Marc.</hi> 9. <hi>Math.</hi> 22.</note> what is that worme venimous, &amp; neuer ceaſing? howe greeuous are thoſe vtwarde darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, alwayes continuing, what are the miniſters appointed for tormentes, which lacking mercie, and without compaſſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue and puniſh? Then they that are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, will gréeuouſly crie vnto the lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.</note> and he wil not héere them. Then ſhall they vnderſtand, that all things, which they had in this lyfe are vaine, and tranſitorie,<note place="margin">Read for this Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes.</note> and ſuch things as they ſuppoſed here to be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, to be founde more bitter than gall, and poyſon. Then where is the pleaſure of the fleſhe, ſo termed falſely?<note place="margin">To feare God is true plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.</note> For there is none other pleaſure, but to feare the lorde. This is the pleaſure, this repleniſheth the ſoule, as it were with marrow, &amp; fatneſſe. Then ſhall they be in deſperation of themſelues, and of the workes, which they haue done, then ſhall they confeſſe and ſaye, that the iudgement of God is true, and righteous, ſaying: did we not héere of this, and yet woulde we not be conuerted from our wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked déedes? But then they ſhall nothing
<pb facs="tcp:7028:65"/> preuaile. Alas y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer I was borne, which am compaſſed about with ſinnes innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, aboue the number of the ſandes. I haue ſinned, but I turne away from them, as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many yron chaines. For my hope is, that I ſhall not ſee my ſinnes aboue in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Vnto whome then ſhall I flie, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, Oh mercifull God, vnto thée I ſay, which forgetteſt, and art not mindefull of iniuries?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> Haue mercie vpon mée, O God, after thy great goodneſſe, according vnto the multitude of thy mercies, doe awaye mine offences. Waſh me thorowly from my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, &amp; clenſe me from my ſinne. For I acknowledge my faultes, &amp; my ſinne is euer before mée. Againſt thee onely haue I ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. I flie vnto thée, for thy great mercie and goodneſſe ſake. I haue prouoked thée, and yet I runne vnto thee, for thy méere pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabilitie. I haue reiected thée, and nowe I come vnto thée, for thy great goodneſſe, and kindneſſe ſake. And I hartily beſéeche thée to turne away thy face from my ſinnes, and blot out al mine offences. Make a cléene hart in mée, O god, &amp; renue a right ſpirit within mée, for thy names ſake onlye. For I haue nothing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye preſent vnto thée, not ſo
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7028:65"/> much as one good worke, not a pure hart,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.</note> but I truſting in thy mercies do wholy commit my ſelf vnto them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſt ſtirre vp in me a prick of conſcience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may not lightly fal againe into ſinne, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may from this time forth, ſerue, and pleaſe thée,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 1.</note> in holineſſe &amp; righteouſneſſe all the dayes of my lyfe. For thine is the kingdome, &amp; the power for euer.</p>
            <p>I beſéech thée therefore, déerely beloued, which hopeſt to obtaine the forgiueneſſe of thy ſinnes, that thou endeuour thy ſelfe to be found in peace, cléene, and without ſpot. If any euill thought come in thy mind, take vp this ſwoorde, that is to wit,<note place="margin">The feare of God is a ſworde.</note> be mindefull of the feare of God, and thou ſhalt cut off al the power of the enimy. And take the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the ſtead of a trumpet. For as the trumpet gathereth the ſouldiers togither: euen ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture crying vnto vs, doth gather togither our thoughts, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord. For our thoughts are euen like ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, which wage warre agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings enimies. And againe, euen as the trumpet ſounding in the time of warre, ſtirreth vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courage of the yong men, battailing againſt their enimies: likewyſe the holy ſcriptures, do rayſe vp thy promptneſſe to vertue, &amp; do
<pb facs="tcp:7028:66"/> make thée valiant againſt affections. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enforce thy ſelf, as much as in thée lieth, oftentymes to apploye the ſcriptures, that they may gather togither thy cogitations, which the enimy hath ſcattred abrode, by his wicked ſubtilty, miniſtring vnto thée nough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty appetites and concupiſcence, or oftentimes alſo bringing aduerſitie, or ſomtimes giuing proſperitie, making thée careleſſe. For he woorketh theſe things by his deceite &amp; guile, that he may ſeperate man from God. For oftentymes it hapneth, that when we can not ouercome and ſubdue one, by concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, then after he offereth vnto him other temptations, thereby to blind his mynd, that he may after find it, an apt ground, to plant in it ſuch things, as pleaſeth him, and in the end, beginneth to miniſter ſuch thoughts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men, that they will ſay with an othe: At what tyme I doe good, I haue infortunate dayes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.</note> Let vs therefore doe euill that thereof may come good. Then if a man be not well aduiſed, he will ſwallow him vp as hell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue. If ſo be that he cannot thus ouercome him, then will he offer vnto him felicity, and ſecuritie of lyfe, and craftily extolleth him, bringing in deceit: an effect of all other moſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7028:66"/> greeuous, and troublous, which is, that he may make him proude, and without feare. This draweth the minde into the bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e of pleaſures. This cauſeth the mouth to ſpeak blaſphemie againſt heauen.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.</note> For it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: They haue ſet, &amp; beſtowed their mouth againſt heauen. This maketh man to bée ignoraunt of God, and not to vnderſtande his owne infirmitie, neyther to thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the daye of death, and iudgement. For this truely is the way of all wickedneſſe. He that reioyſeth to walke in this waye, that is to wit, of proſperitie, and cockering, ſhall in the ende come into the ſtorehouſe of death. This is the waye whereof the lorde ſayed: Wyde, and broad is the way,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> which leadeth vnto deſtruction. Beholde thou haſt heard, wherefore the enimie endeuoreth ſometime to bring vs proſperitie, ſometime aduerſity. For as he proueth the minde of man, which ſtruggeleth, and ſtriueth againſt him, to be affected: euen ſo by his malignitie, doth he furniſhe his hoſte againſt him. Therfore be ſober, and warie, and alwayes giue thy ſelfe vnto reading, that thou mayeſt learne, how it behoueth thée, to eſchue the ſnares of that enimie, and to take hold on euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:7028:67"/> lyfe. For the reading of holy ſcripture, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the wandring minde to ſtande faſt, and giueth hir the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">God is knowne out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Read for this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſecond epiſtle to Timothi. The holy ghoſt ſpeaketh in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note>Thou heareſt how that he, which with an vnfained hart ymployeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures, receyueth the knowledge of God. Nelect not therefore thy ſelfe, but ymploy reading, and prayer, that thy mind may be lightned, that thou mayeſt be made perfite, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in all things, wanting in no point. Let others boaſt of the fréendſhip of honorable men, princes, and kings. But reioyce thou before the angelles of God, ſpeaking vnto him, and to the holye ghoſt, by the ſacred ſcriptures.<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> For the holye ghoſt is he, that ſpeaketh by them.<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.</note> Doe thy diligence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſtantly to be occupied in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and prayers. For looke how often thou art conuerſant with God by them: ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten is thy bodye and ſoule ſanctified. Then take this for certeintie, that when thou hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneſt to reade the ſcriptures, thou art ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Therfore do thy good will, oftentimes to imploy them. Although thy handes be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied: yet mayeſt thou praye in thy minde. For bleſſed Anne,<note place="margin">God is to be praied vnto with the mind. 1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 1.</note> Samuell the prophet his mother, prayed, and moued but hir lippes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7028:67"/> onely, yet hir prayers entered into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eares of the God of Sabaoth, &amp; ſhe obtained y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing ſhée deſired. Therefore although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hands be otherwiſe buſied, yet praye thou, at the leaſt wiſe with thy minde. For God heareth euen the ſilent. If thou haue no ſkill to read,<note place="margin">He that cannot reade, or vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not what he readeth, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort vnto ſome wiſe man.</note> yet reſort where thou mayſt heare, and take profite thereof. For it is written:<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sirach.</hi> 6.</note> If thou ſée a wiſe man, go thou vnto him early in the morning, and let thy foote tread the path vnto his gate. For this counſell is not only good for them, that cannot reade, but alſo for them that can. For many there be, which read, and know not what they read. Take héede therefore, that thou doe not little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, the<note n="*" place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> grace beſtowed on thée by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frée gift of Chriſt: but be thou carefull to ſéeke, how thou mayeſt pleaſe the lorde, that thou mayeſt procure, and get vnto thée, the bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of his ſaintes. For it is written: Bleſſed are they,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> which keepe his teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and ſeeke him with their whole hart. See that the enimie let thée not, that when thou wouldſt read, he make thée ſlouthfull, and put other buſineſſe in thy heade, which ſhall pull thée awaye, ſaying: Firſt finiſhe thou theſe ſmall affaires, and ſo ſhalt thou
<pb facs="tcp:7028:68"/> reade without trouble of minde. For howe often ſendeth he in thoſe things, that maye encourage thée vnto handie labour: And he obiecteth ſuch matters, that he may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſooner withhold thée from reading, being the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter profite. For as much as, the deuill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing man to be diſpoſed to reade, ſetteth againſt him by theſe, and other lyke occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, ſeeking if he may by any meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, let him: yet co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ent thou not vnto him, but be euen as the Hart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.</note> which thirſteth, and deſireth to come vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water ſprings, that is to ſay, vnto the holy ſcriptures, that thou mayeſt drinke out of them ſuch things, as are méete and profitable for thée, as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. When it is giuen thée to know any ſentence, let it not eſcape thée, but pouder vpon it in thy minde, write in thine hart, and thou ſhalt kéepe it, neuer able to bée raſed out of thy memorie. For it is written: I will thinke vpon thy righteouſneſſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> And againe: I haue hidde thy words within my hart, that I ſhoulde not ſinne againſt thée. And in an other place: Wherewith ſhall a yong man clenſe his waye? Euen by ruling himſelfe after thy worde. For who is he, that is mindefull of the worde of the lorde,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7028:68"/> and amendeth not his wayes? Is not hée alwaies a reprobate, &amp; a caſt awaye caytife, which remembereth nothing, but rather forgetteth that, which he once knew? True<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God ſayth vnto ſuch an one.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> Wherefore talkeſt thou of my righteouſneſſe, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt my teſtimony in thy mouth? Whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he commaundeth that thing to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from him, which he ſéemeth to haue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 25.</note> And what was there commaunded to bée taken from him, which he ſéemed to haue? Faith. For he calleth himſelfe a chriſtian,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.</note> but denyeth it in his déedes, and he is worſe than an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidell. And therefore he commaundeth the holy ghoſt to be taken from him, which he receyued in the daye of his redemption, and that he ſéemed to haue alſo. And ſuch a man ſhal become like vnto a wine veſſell, thorow the which the wine is ſpilte and loſt, &amp; they that ſée him know it not, ſuppoſing him to he full, but when wine ſhoulde be drawen out of him, then he appéereth vnto all men to be emptie. Therefore euen ſo, ſuch a man ſhall appéere emptie in the daye of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and his déedes ſhall be manifeſt vnto all the world. And ſuch are they, which wil ſaye vnto the king in that day:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> Lorde haue
<pb facs="tcp:7028:69"/> not we propheſied in thy name? and haue done many great things in thy name? And the king will anſwere, and ſaye vnto them: Verily I ſaye vnto you, I knowe you not. Thou ſeeſt, déerely beloued, that ſuch a man hath nothing at all. Be thou therfore mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the worde of God, and amende thy lyfe. Beware thou ſuffer not the birdes to deſcende, and deuoure the ſeede of the ſonne of God. For he himſelfe ſaide, that the ſéede is the worde which ye haue heard.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 13.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hide thou the ſéede in the ſorowes of thy lande, that is to wit, hide the worde in the middell of thine hart, that thou mayeſt bring forth ſome fruit vnto the lord in feare. And when thou readeſt, read diligently, and boldly, and handle eche lyne, moderatly conſidering thereof. Endeuor not to reade ouer many leaues, but if any obſcure ſenſe happen vnto thée, let it not gréeue thée to pervſe the verſe twice or thrice, vntill thou vnderſtande the meaning, and force thereof. Furthermore, when thou prepareſt thy ſelfe to ſit downe, and read, or to heare an other: firſt praye vnto God ſaying thus:<note place="margin">Scripture is attent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfely to be reade with pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.</note> O lorde Ieſu Chriſt, open myne eyes, and the eares of my hart, that they may heare thy words,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7028:69"/> and vnderſtande them, and may, O lorde, fulfill thy wyll, hide not thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from me, bicauſe I am a ſtraunger on the earth, but open, and diſcouer mine eyes, and I will conſider the maruellous things of thy lawe. For in thée, Oh my God, haue I truſted, that thou ſhouldſt ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mine hart. Alſo I beſéeche thée ſo praye vnto God alwaies, that he will illuminate thy minde, and open vnto thée the effect, and force of his worde. For many haue erred,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> counted themſelues wiſe, they became fooles, not vnderſtanding what was written, and falling into blaſphemies, haue therein peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Therfore, if thou in reading finde any thing hard to be vnderſtoode, take héede the enimy teach thée not to ſay within thy ſelfe, it is not ſo, as this word expreſſeth (for how ſhould it be ſo?) and ſuche lyke. But if thou beléeue God, beléeue his word alſo, and ſay vnto the enimie: Come behinde me ſathan. For I know thée not. The worde of God is a pure worde, as tryed ſiluer, clenſed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.</note> and purged from the earth ſeauen folde, and in it, is no peruerſe matter, other elſe haulting, as the prouerbe is, but all things therein ſéeme good in the wiſe mans ſight, and are
<pb facs="tcp:7028:70"/> righteous before them, that finde know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and I truely am a foole, and knowe not the ſcriptures, but well vnderſtande, they are ſpiritually written. For the apoſtle ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</note> that the lawe is ſpirituall. Then looke vp towardes heauen, ſaying theſe wordes: Lorde I beleue thy worde, and doe not gaine ſay it, but I truſt in the worde of thy holy ſpirite. Preſerue me therefore, O lorde, that I may finde fauour in thy ſight. For I ſéeke none other thing, but only to be ſaued. Oh mercifull father, that I maye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy grace, and fauour. For thine is the kingdome, and mercie for euer, and euer. Amen.</p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>Peroratio.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beſéeche you therefore brethren, déerely beloued in the lorde, that ye endeuour your ſelues to haue theſe things daylie in memorie, I meane, faith, hope, charitie, and humilitie, that they may be ſealed vp by prayers vnto God, and meditations of holy ſcriptures. For if you haue thoſe things, and doe abound in them, they will not leaue you emptie, and barren touching the knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7028:70"/> For the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man, which hath not thoſe things, but neglecteth his owne ſaluation, is blind, groping the waye with his hande,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1.</note> forgetting that he is cleanſed from his olde ſinnes, and it ſhall happen vnto him, as it is ſayde in the true prouerbe:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2.</note> The dogge is returned againe vnto his domite, and the waſhed ſwine vnto his dur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie puddle. They therefore,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 2.</note> that haue eſcaped the pollutions of the worlde, as it is written, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced them in there baptiſme, and are come vnto the knowledge of our lord Ieſus Chriſt, and are afterwards againe entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with them, there ende ſhall bée worſe, than there beginning. For it had bene bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them, not to haue knowne the waye of truth, then when they haue knowne it, to returne backe againe vnto the things, which were forſaken. Let vs therfore, being the déere and faythfull ſeruauntes of God, and his chriſtian choſen ſouldiours, diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and earneſtly take vp the foreſaide ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in oure hartes, and not haue them in minde by an outwarde ſhowe, that we battayling well, and treading downe al the power of the enimie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 3.</note> may be deliuered from the curſe to come vpon the children of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beléefe,
<pb facs="tcp:7028:71"/> and that we maye finde grace,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4.</note> and mercie in that horrible daye, before the iuſt iudge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.</note> which will rewarde euerie man, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his déedes, to whome, with the almightie father, and the holy ſpirite, belongeth honor, and glory, now, and for euer, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:71"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PHiſick for the ſoule, verie neceſſarie to be vſed in the agony of death, and in theſe extreme and moſt perillous ſeaſons. &amp;c. folio. 1.</item>
               <item>Faith is chiefely neceſſarie for the ſick, to abide the paines of the bodye, and the temptations, wherwith he is peſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. folio. 3.</item>
               <item>The articles of our faith are diligently to be conſidered of the ſick. folio. 5</item>
               <item>Wherefore ſickneſſes are ſent vnto vs from God. folio. 5</item>
               <item>There be three things, which torment vs moſt greeuouſly, and cruelly, and doe trouble oure mindes in the agonie of death, that is to wit, ſinne, death, hell, or damnation. folio. 8</item>
               <item>¶A prayer for the ſame. folio. 8</item>
               <item>What is to bee done, when ſinne doth vexe, and ſtirre our conſciences. folio. 9</item>
               <item>The teſtimonies of ſcripture for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes through Chriſt, muſt be diligently repeated vnto the ſick. &amp;c. folio. 11</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7028:72" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>Whether the ſick may lawfully ſeke the phiſitions helpe, and vſe phiſicke, or no. folio. 18</item>
               <item>What is to be done, when death bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth terror, and feare vpon vs. folio. 18</item>
               <item>The teſtimonies of ſcripture, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead. folio. 20</item>
               <item>We will adde alſo, other ſentences of ſcripture, conteyning plentifull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. folio. 23</item>
               <item>What is to be done, when hell, or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall damnation, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming in our minds, doth feare vs. folio. 25</item>
               <item>Of the making of a teſtament, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of ſinnes vnto God. folio. 34</item>
               <item>Of the ſacrament of the lords ſupper. folio. 35</item>
               <item>The ſorow, which many take, more then is requiſite; for the death of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and frendes, ought to be tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the right rule of reaſon. folio. 37</item>
               <item>A precept contayning an exhortation vnto al them, which profeſſe the name of Chriſt. folio. 39</item>
               <item>Peroratio. folio. 40</item>
               <item>A fourme, and methode, or right order to comfort the ſick. folio. 41</item>
            </list>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:7028:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
